<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevv age of old names. By Ios. Wib. Master of Artes of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
            <author>Wybarne, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120434</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855631</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855631</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1056:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevv age of old names. By Ios. Wib. Master of Artes of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                  <author>Wybarne, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 133, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for William Barret, and Henry Fetherstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Ios. Wybarne.</note>
                  <note>Essays.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEW AGE OF OLD NAMES.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ioſ. Wib.</hi> Maſter of Artes of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>William Barret,</hi> and <hi>Henry Fetherſtone.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, HIS Moſt worthy friend, Sir IOHN WENTVVORTH <hi>Knight,</hi> Health and Happineſſe now and for euer.</head>
            <opener>Parue, nec inuideo, ſine me Liber ibis in Aulam,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as <hi>Tanais</hi> goes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Meotis,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeus</hi> vnder the Sea, yet neither is the one bitter, nor the other ſalt: So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubt not but that thoſe vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb facs="tcp:21132:3"/> imputations, which the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents cast vpon the Court, ſhall neuer attaint nor arreſt your heroycke ſpirit, which as it hath vouchſafed to ſhine vpon me with gracious aſpect (for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly true Nobilitie and Humilitie, are like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> twinnes:) So hath it in forſt me to eleuate my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Orbe of my actiuitie, and with the Eagle to lay my Egges in the lap of <hi>loue:</hi> Theſe I most humbly commend to your powerfull loue. I could wiſh ſome <hi>Caſtor</hi> or <hi>Pollux</hi> were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſhell, and if it pleaſe you, with the influence of your Sphere, to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſome Celeſtiall heate in them, I hope the yong ones, if they proue ſinging Birds, will learne to ſing the Song of gratitude to your munificence, if they be Birds of pray, I will charge them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="tcp:21132:3"/> your game. If they be fowles, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate to <hi>Ruc</hi> the god of Hungarie, I will deſire no more, but that they may pleaſe your palate: moſt humbly I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your Worſhip, not to breake them, for they are not the eggs of a Cocatrice: trie the ſucceſſe, my deſire is, that they may proue Cockes of the game. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> ſet vp a prize for Poetrie, which he kept euery fift yeare, and had his cruelty beene as little, as his wit was great, hee would haue beene as much commended for this, as hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for other actions: but I truſt I ſhall finde you tobelike his Brother <hi>Titus,</hi> in whoſegreatneſſe nothing was vnpleaſant, but the ſhortneſſe: Now therfore as <hi>Perſeus</hi> defended himſelfe vnder the buckler of <hi>Pallace,</hi> and <hi>Teucer</hi> vnder that of <hi>Aiax:</hi> ſo I leaue
<pb facs="tcp:21132:4"/> mine orphant Muſe to the ingenu ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of your Honourable nature, and the Patronage of your deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued greatneſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips alwayes at commaund Joſ. Wybarne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, if I may perſwade, reade the booke before the Epiſtle; for this latter is the quotient, the former is the Diuiſion: if thou wilt cenſure it before thou haſt read it, it may be ſome other <hi>Harpie</hi> will light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy bookes, if thou write any, and if thou write none, I will anſwere thee with the Poet of <hi>Bilbilis,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carpere vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which one thus ſimply turned: Either commend mee, or come mend me: and peraduenture I ſhall requeſt thee as <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> did the Embaſſador, not to tell how I played with my childe, till thou haſt one of thine owne, if thou lookeſt for newes, you may doe well to goe to the Colonie at Virginia: if for deepe matter, ſtay till my head bee of ſiluer, for golden heades commonly bring forth but leaden works: if for ſtrange and vncoth ſtraines of wit, know that I care not for Apricocks, <hi>hoe eſt, ingenia praecocia:</hi> I haue ſeene many of their bookes ſhrinke in the wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: if thou require more accurate teſtimonies, the matter is morall and Poſitiue, not demonſtratiue or controuerſiall: for I ſuppoſe, that the bramble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie hath been a meanes to choake moſt of our
<pb facs="tcp:21132:5"/> ſciences, which ſtand more on explication of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then in winding and windy arguments, if I haue omitted ſomething in a matter ſo variable, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I talke of <hi>Errors Denne,</hi> celebrated by the penne of our ſecond <hi>Chaucer.</hi> Laſtly, conſider I haue put an olde ſong to a new tune, if thou like it not, harken to the Harmonie of the Planets, which if thou canſt not heare, thinke thou wert borne at the fall of Nilus: and thus wiſhing thee eyther to open thy eares with courteſie, or ſhut them with ſilence: I leaue vnto thee this my Grammer, wherein I haue handled <hi>Nomen</hi> and <hi>Pronomen,</hi> other parts of ſpeech I am not at leyſure now to decline.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>ESt Latio in medio late lacus, vndi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> opaco</l>
               <l>Vmbraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrepitu, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vndanti ſulphure inhorr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</l>
               <l>Errorum ſtatio eſt: at Graio murmure Auernus:</l>
               <l>Hic mille anguipedum vultus, noua nomina rerum</l>
               <l>Apparent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> immanis hiatibus Hydra:</l>
               <l>Hinc ſomno torpens, gelido<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> papauere Morpheus,</l>
               <l>Ter gemina hinc Hecate, tria virginis ora <hi>Dianae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et trino Anguicomus collatrans ianitor ore,</l>
               <l>Virtuteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Arteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; verſicoloribus armis,</l>
               <l>Publicolaeque doli, ac Stoici dumeta veratri,</l>
               <l>Religio intorti ſquamis ſinuata Colubri,</l>
               <l>Et quaecunque latent informi monſtra Barathro,</l>
               <l>Pallados augurio demum haec Camerina mouetur,</l>
               <l>Id ſortes memorant Liciae, ac iubet author <hi>Apollo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tantae molis erit ſuetos gracileſcere nimbos,</l>
               <l>Diſcite iuſtitiam moniti, ac non temnere technas.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21132:5"/>
            <head>THE NEWE AGE OF OLD NAMES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That nothing is knowen but Names.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the bodyworke not without the ſpirit, yet the ſpirit is either compelled, or inclined, or rather declined to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill actions, by the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the body; wherefore they that handle Aſtrology, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomie, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke: proceede ſometime certainly, and alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably; becauſe of the mutuall ſympathy and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorceable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21132:6"/> dependance of the ſoule and bodie: the like proportions are to be found in ſpeech, wherein the vowels reſemble the ſoule, the conſonants the bodie: the greateſt vigor of ſpeech is ſeene in names, concerning which wee will declare: firſt, that all knowledge comes by deduction of them: ſecondly, that all error ariſeth from ſeduction by them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>NOw then it is certaine, that as it is in the fable of the Foxe, which licked onely the outſide of the glaſſe, but could not come to the pottage, ſo we know names, but not things: This was ſignified of old by them that told, how <hi>Iupiter</hi> wasfed with bones<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ucian dialog. of Iupiter and Prometheus.</note> and fat, <hi>Prometheus</hi> reſeruing vnto himſelfe the ſolid fleſh: by the fleſh is meant ſound knowledge, by the fat the fleeting ſhew of ſuperficiarie tearmes of Arte, by the bones is deciphered, the inextricable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed labour in the curioſities of euerſtriuing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, So <hi>Ixion</hi> imbracing a cloud for <hi>Iuno<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and <hi>Narciſſus</hi> louing his owne ſhadowe for a water <hi>Nymph,</hi> and Paris maintaining the Troian warre in<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ripid. in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>na. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eophron in Caſſandra.</note> the defence of <hi>Helenaes</hi> Idoll, for <hi>Helena</hi> her ſelfe was conueied by <hi>Iuno</hi> to <hi>Proteus</hi> King of Egypt: All theſe declare that we are fedde with the ſhales, not with the kernels of learning, and as the common by-word goeth, whileſt the blind and the lame man<note place="margin">Herodotus in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fe of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</note> haue for their portions the ſhels of the Oyſter, the Lawyers fees is the fleſh of the fiſh. To conclude
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21132:6"/> this truth by no fabulous truthes, conſider that true<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tamor. 5. lib. Claudian de raptu Proſerpinae</note> fable of <hi>Proſerpina,</hi> wherein it is auouched, that ſhee for eating ſeuen graines of a Pomegranat in the Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian garden, was made the Queene of Hell, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of this Muthologie, the Turkiſh Prieſts in their Alcaron doe giue vs light: for they ſay, that the forbidden fruite was a Pomegranat, and that euery graine therein was of the quantitie of an egge. The Frenchmen at this day call a Peache, <hi>vn peche,</hi> which they deriue a <hi>peccando,</hi> as the Latines <hi>malum</hi> for an Apple hath great affinitie, with <hi>malum</hi> for euill, now ſhe that taſted this Apple, was before her fall<note place="margin">Plutarch. de I ſide &amp; Oſiride</note> tearmed <hi>Iſha,</hi> the Egyptians ignorantly called her <hi>Iſis,</hi> which name <hi>Plutarch</hi> expoundeth, to ſignifie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and this was the knowledge of good and euill, of good by depriuation, of euill by deprauation, and late repenting experience, the higheſt note whereof is to know, <hi>That we know nothing but Names.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THis aſſertion we ſhall now bring to the hammer, the Anuell, and the touchſtone: namely to firme reaſon, the firſt agument is this; euery thing is either a ſubſtance or an accident, the ſubſtance is a Wood,<note place="margin">See Zabar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll vpon the firſt of the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. cap. 4.</note> peirſable by no ſtarre, for all demonſtration is of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, ſeeing that the <hi>maior terminus,</hi> is a proper effect the <hi>minor</hi> is the ſubiect, the middle extreame is the cauſe efficient or finall: likewiſe all definitions are of accidents, for as much as they are inquired onely by demonſtration,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21132:7"/> which indeed is to be turned into a definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as we ſee in the nature of the Silke-worme, the Egge becomes a Worme, and the Worme in time a Flie, ſo a demonſtration by altering of termes is made a definition: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e example will explaine all. Where the Earth is interpoſed, there is a depriuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of light, or an Eclips, but betweene the Moone and Sunne, the Earth is interpoſed, in the Moone therefore there is an Eclips. From this reall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration by an vnfabling Metamorphoſis: wee collect this definition, an Eclips is the depriuation of light in the Moone, made by the interpoſition of the Earth betweene her and the Sunne, by this it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that accidents only can be demonſtrated and defin'd: Now euery accident is either quantitie, qualitie, action, paſſion, or relation which laſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a terme or name impoſed by Art, and is extracted from the foundation of the fower former accidents, as great and little, from quantitie, better and worſe, from qualitie, Father and Sonne, from action and paſſion, now it ſhall appeare that wee know nothing but relations, and conſequently no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but naked names. This is firſt euident in all quantities which by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> are reputed fiue, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, Time, Place, Number, Speech, as the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of Sillables is therein conſidered, Magnitude is length, breadth, thickneſſe, now to leaue the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians to there nightly ſpeculations, I requeſt all actiue wits to tell me, what doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey vnderſtand in length, but a certaine name of difference from breadth and thickneſſe, and what is Magnitude but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21132:7"/> an accident of the matter, how can be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from the forme by an eſſentiall difference, conſidering difference of difference cannot be aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, except we will runne out into infinite <hi>Laborin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</hi> And as for Time is it ought, but a name re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue of that which is paſt and to come? So that certainely about this flower or rather about the ſmel thereof, many haue diſtilled out the flower of their beſt Time: Concerning Place, it hath ſo many bones, that we haue neede of Cranes to plucke them out of the throates of Philoſophers, <hi>Scaliger</hi> after<note place="margin">Exercitio. 6.</note> many <hi>Maeanders</hi> and excurſions ſaith, <hi>Locus eſt vacui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Corporis ſubituri,</hi> Place is an emptineſſe capable of a body that ſhall enter or ſucceede. I pray you what is this but <hi>Maedeaes</hi> emptie Casket ſetting <hi>Cryu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> with her houſe on fire. Now for Number, it is moſt ſpent in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phers, places, names. Laſtly for Speech, what ſinewes can wee expect from it, is it<note place="margin">Odyſſ. 11.</note> not like the Ghoſt in <hi>Homer:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For now no longer ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>wes hold,</l>
                     <l>The fleſh and bones beene waxen old.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Thus much of Quantitie: Now Qualitie conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all in Degrees, which are nothing but reſpects, reſpects are nothing but relations relations nothing but Names, as for Action and Paſſion, they are ſo meerely Relatiue, that <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaith, they differ no more then the way from Thebes to Athens, and<note place="margin">Phyſ. 3. lib. cap. 3.</note> from Athens to Thebes. Thence we conclude, that as the Thunder many times deſtroyeth the ſword, leauing the ſcabberd vntoucht, ſo the ſubſtance and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21132:8"/> realitie of all knowledge is ſuckt out, like the egges of the Crocadile by the Icnumon, and nothing left for our inheritance but ſhels, ſheathes and Names.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond argument or plea may bee thus fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to proue that we haue nothing but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels skinne ſtuft with Hay, as <hi>Semiramis</hi> did againſt the King of India, either wee knowe the beeing, (which nice wits haue called the eſſence) or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of being, which Scholemen abounding with leaſure, rather then learning, haue called exiſtence, the being is vnknowen like the head of Nilus in the mount Atlas, for who dares auer, that he knowes the matter and forme of an accident, except hee would be confined to the Iſle of Antiſera, to haue his braine purged with <hi>Helibore:</hi> as for the exiſtence or mnaner of ſubſiſting, is it not a notionall and relatiue terme? cramming a man with learning, as promiſes doe with hope, and what bee termes, but names? So that to conclude, as in the Citie of Butus, they that<note place="margin">Herodotus in Euterpe.</note> conſulted with the Oracle of Latona, after they had ſlept before her Image, did by the firſt word of the next that met them, gather a prediction: ſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculine promiſes of reall knowledge are made, we are turned off at laſt with Feminine performance, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of words, ſo that the diſtinction of the two Sects of Schoole-men, reall, and nominall, is now confounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21132:8"/>
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>THe third reaſon doth thus ratifie the matter:<note place="margin">Exercitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 307. Sect. 21.</note> All knowledge is by <hi>ſpecies</hi> and ſhewes, called intelligible, which are prooued by <hi>Scaliger</hi> to bee meere accidents, but if we ſift it further, we ſhall find them to be nothing but Names or Notions, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the vnderſtanding: for colours, ſounds, ſmels, taſtes, and qualities of touching, offering themſelues to the common ſenſe, are carried into the inner cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of the phanſie, in whoſe myrror they are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the ſimple vnderſtanding, which firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing them as ſingle termes, maketh of them ſeuen Spiders-webs: firſt compounding and diuiding, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly reaſoning and diſcourſing, thirdly reſting or agreeing, fourthly deliberating and conſulting, fiftly chuſing, ſixtly reflecting by the facultie of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, laſtly deſiring and mouing. So that to gather the totall ſumme, theſe <hi>ſpecies,</hi> which we call intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, are but termes gathered into ſundry formes, as of the ſame watrie vapour are made many meteors, a Cloud, a Raine-bow, the Rods, the Crowne, pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins; alſo raine, haile and ſnow: ſo of the ſame names variably framed, iſſue not new things, but new ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, by this it is cleare that the <hi>Quotum</hi> of all our knowledge conſiſteth in a ſmall number of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken names, which we may call <hi>reliquias Danaum, atque immitis Achilli:</hi> the reliques of mans fall, wherein the wings of the ſoule were ſo clipped, that were they not repaired by <hi>Dedalus,</hi> who hath his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21132:9"/> name from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to know, ſhee ſhould alwaies haue flagged vpon the fennes of baſe mortalitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VI.</head>
                  <p>THe laſt reaſon of this quaternion of Souldiers, may thus be demonſtrated, all knowledge is by ſome argument, for the Latine <hi>arguere</hi> to argue, is deduced from the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, white or cleere, whence is drawen <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>argentum,</hi> Siluer, it is now not materiall, whoſe method wee inſiſt vpon, whether of <hi>Ramus</hi> the bough, or <hi>Aristotle</hi> the roote, by either clew we may get out of the laborinth, let vs therefore aſſume for example ſake, any ſort of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as <hi>cauſa, cauſatum,</hi> vulgarly called <hi>effectum Subiectum, accidens,</hi> lately intituled <hi>adiunctum,</hi> and we ſhall find that all their knowledge is by relation of termes. For as all men acknowledge there bee fower cauſes, Efficient, Matter, Forme, End, ſo the moſt learned haue form'd fower <hi>cauſata</hi> or products of cauſes, <hi>Effectum, Materiatum, Formatum, Deſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which doe mutually anſwere to the cauſes, like the cords of Muſicke, and what are theſe but Names and new notions? The ſame may be obſerued in the proportionable differences of <hi>Subiectum</hi> &amp; <hi>Accidens.</hi> For as at <hi>Philbets</hi> in Egypt, of Camels dung and a ſoft fire, they make Chickens to bee hatcht from Egges, which are there ſet: ſo mans mind being well tempered, from one relatiue terme frameth another, farre ſurmounting both the skil and felicitie of them,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21132:9"/> which extract the ſpirit of Roſes, Wine, yea and all Chimicall impoſtures. Shall we thinke the like is not to bee ſeene in Arguments of leſſe moment? what be reaſons drawen from diſagreeing, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, from Name, diuiſion, definition, teſtimonie; but a heape of Aenigmaticall termes, ouergrowne with diſtinctions, as <hi>Archymedes</hi> Tombe was with<note place="margin">Tuſcul. Queſ. 5. lib.</note> Thornes, when <hi>Cicero</hi> came to viſit it. Wherefore if all knowledge be of Accidents, and thoſe are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, if we onely know the maner of being, not the being of things in nature, if all ſhewes intelligible, and Arguments, be but Accidents in relation, that is meere Names, it remaineth that we onely feede vpon the Thiſtles of Names, howſoeuer we ſeeme to carie vpon our backs moſt precious Merchandiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Knots ſought in a Bul-ruſh.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue hitherto lent one eare to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant,<note place="margin">VVater with Romanes, as with vs the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ower Glaſſe. Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tonius in Claudio.</note> the accuſer is now to bee heard, we are to allow him ſufficient water to pleade by, Firſt then he reaſoneth againſt vs thus: We know God as we are taught, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all knowledge is not of Names. But ſtay pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous man, caſt down thy eyes from thy traine to thy feete, ſpeake not <hi>De numine ſine lumine,</hi> talke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21132:10"/> not of God without God, canſt thou know him but by his workes, thou mayeſt indeede belieue aboue reaſon, but wilt thou emptie his Ocean into thy Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, canſt thou diuine how the begetter ſhould not be before him that is begotten, canſt thou dreame how generation and proceeding differ, doth not the Spirit worke like the Wind, whoſe ſound thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 8.</note> but knowes not whence it comes, or whether it goes! In a word, if thou beleeueſt with reuerence thou ſhalt one day know him face to face, but now thou knoweſt him onely in a Riddle, and well is it for thee, if thou knoweſt his Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>BVt now like <hi>Hanibal</hi> or <hi>Mithridates</hi> once ouer come, this aduerſarie recollecteth his forces, and thus pleadeth the ſecond time. Know you not that the Skepticke doctrine of <hi>Pyrrho, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ston,</hi> and <hi>Hiril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> hath beene lone agoe hiſt out of the Schooles or rather baniſht and confined among the Barbari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans, will you cauſe vs to doubt of all things, then ſhall we doubt, whether you doubt or no, tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble you may carrie bread in the one hand, and a ſtone in the other, and that you may ſpeake as falſe as an Almanacke maker, though you meane as true, as a man vpon his death bed. <hi>Staffords</hi> Law muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you, if you be poſſeſt with this frenzie, but oh my friend haue me not to Bedlam, it may be I haue ſold my Land, which you meane to begge. I an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21132:10"/> in a word, I am no Skepticke, nor I hope you no Gnoſticke, I doubt not whether I know, but know reſoluedly, that I doe not know any thing but Names whereupon to reſolue. They that came<note place="margin">Ariſtotle Mund. Cap. 1.</note> to <hi>Athens</hi> the firſt yeere were wiſe men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſecond yeere Philoſophers, that is louers of Wiſedome: The third yeere Rhetoritians, that is meere bable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, The meaning is, Firſt, they deemed themſelues to be wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, caſting vp Mountaines to heauen, like the Sonnes of <hi>Aeolus.</hi> After feeling themſelues to bee puft with a timpany of Pride, they deſired that to be<note place="margin">Metamor. 11.</note> in themſelues which they admired in others: Laſtly ſeeing the more they ſtrayed, the leſſe they could goe backe, they found a Harueſt of wild corne was left them, it may be of thoſe Reedes which <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> Barber filled full of words, neither is this ſpoken of modeſt hypocriſie or glory in holding Paradoxes. For when I ſay that we know Names, I aſcribe ſuch a meaſure of knowledge to mans ſhallow veſſel, as it is hardly capable of, for are not Names drawne from the cauſes, effects, ſubiects, and accidents, which like the fower Riuers of the Moone, <hi>Rhenus, Danubius, Nylus,</hi> and <hi>Ganges,</hi> are ſtored with endleſſe plentie of wholſome waters? Some haue not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſay, that Names are taken by <hi>Antiphraſis</hi> from the contrary, as <hi>Parca quod min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> parcat, Lucus quod non luceat,</hi> but this counterfeit <hi>Antiphraſis</hi> is now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſed, doth not the <hi>Parca</hi> ſpare, when two produce the life, and onely one cutteth it off: May not <hi>lucus</hi> be drawne a <hi>luce,</hi> ſeeing it is a Groue ſhining with the torches of heathen Idols, neither ſhall we feare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21132:11"/> barrenneſſe, becauſe we haue no Baſtards, or lacke of Names, becauſe we want <hi>Antiphraſis:</hi> To conclude then, though we know nothing but Names, yet by them as the Vines doe by their <hi>Palmites,</hi> wee lay hold on the Elme, that is, we doe ſee the backe parts of things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>I Had thought by this time that <hi>Cerberus</hi> would haue coucht, but with his third head hee barkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thus, All Artes, but eſpecially Sciences, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>end the knowledge of things, therefore to ſerue vs like yonger brethren with Legacies of meere names, and to bereaue vs of the Gauell-kind Land, is to ſhew that you are a ſelfe-louer without a Corriuall: But ſtay my friend, let it be firſt manifeſt that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left Land, and then we wil rather agree at home, then ſuffer the Butlets boxe to winne all. <hi>Agrippa</hi> in his Booke <hi>Devanitate Scientiarum &amp; Viues,</hi> whoſe fame euer liues in his Booke <hi>De cauſis corruptarum Artium,</hi> will ſoone purge thee of this ſwelling error: but experience in euery Art, and the ſequell of this Treatiſe, ſhal in part aſwage thy hunger, except thou haue <hi>Canina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appetentiam,</hi> ſuch a hunger as <hi>Eriſicthon</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Metamorp. 12.</note> had, which was maintained by his daughters Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſing, that is by her whoredome, as learned men expound it: But now enough of this Problem, for they that are wiſe know it already, and fooles wil not vnderſtand it, though you bray them like <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archus</hi> in an Iron morter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21132:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The error by names in Policie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing ſufficiently to the vnlearned, and ſuperficially to the iudicious de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared, that our knowledge is onely of Names, it remaineth that we manifeſt errors which come by Names, for ſo this new Age of Old Names will be detected. For as the Speare of <hi>Achilles</hi> did both wound and heale <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liphus,</hi> and as the water of <hi>Dodona</hi> doth both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh and lighten Torches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo Names both teach and ſeduce: many ſpices are ſaid to bee cold in tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and hot in working; that is in applying, as when they are beaten, eaten or diſgeſted: ſo Names if they be but nakedly touched, pricke and ſting like nettles, but if they be more roughly examined, they bring no damage nor deceit; and firſt this is plaine in matter of policie: the yron gouernment of the Romanes may bee a preſident for all: Firſt when <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neas</hi> had ouercome <hi>Turnus,</hi> to appeaſe the mind of the <hi>Hetrurians</hi> and Latines whom he conquered, he was content that the name of Troians ſhould bee abrogated, &amp; reſted ſatisfied with thoſe names which he found in Italy: as if now the Kings Maieſtie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of Scotland into England; ſhould to the further vniting of both the Realmes, call them by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21132:12"/> the auncient name of Britanie, and ſtile himſelfe King of Great Britaine, as <hi>Alphred</hi> and ſome aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Princes haue done: next <hi>Romulus,</hi> when the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines were vnited to him, was content that the name of <hi>Tatienſes</hi> ſhould remaine, and that <hi>Tatius</hi> ſhould enioy the name of a King, though it appeared not long after, that as ſmall Brookes falling into a great riuer looſe their name, ſo this weake ſtarre concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the <hi>Sol</hi> that would be <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us,</hi> ſoone ſuffered both a totall and finall Eclips, for to ſay no more, the murther of <hi>Tatius</hi> by <hi>Romulus</hi> his craftie conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence, was not reuenged: the like is obſerued in <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Hoſtilius,</hi> the third king of Rome, who ſuffered that the Albanes ſhould looſe their name, though they were his Countrimen, yet withall he infranc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in the liberties of Rome: But to leaue Kings. When the Romans had vomited out the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous broode of <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> they found out a new Name, for inſtead of one King, they had two Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuls, and withall enacted a Law, that as the name of Tyrant in old time, ſo now the name of King among them, ſhould be for euer held moſt odious and omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and withal they baniſhed <hi>Collatinus Tarquinius</hi> onely for the name ſake, though indeed he was one of the firſt that conſpired againſt the tyrant, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was this law tranſitorie, for <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> fiue hundred yeeres after, could by no meanes obtaine the name of King, though he were not ſecond to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, either in authoritie or policie: and yet <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar</hi> rather by the length of time, then ſtrength of wit; did in this kind miniſter ſundry ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21132:12"/> as is at large to be ſeene in <hi>Appian</hi> and <hi>Dion:</hi> to name all, were more then tedious, and yet to leaue all, would leaue this Remonſtrance too naked.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AVguſtus</hi> therefore finding that the name of king was odious, and the terme of <hi>Dictator</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked or ſuſpected, forged a new name of Emperour, and ſo put away the title, but not the power of a<note place="margin">Si Catulos Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp;c.</note> kingdome; not vnlike (if we may compare whelpes with dogges) to her that hauing denied a yong man twiſe, finding him not to renue his ſuite, told him by letter, two Negatiues make an Affirmatiue, and ſo with her louing Logicke ſhe entertained him againe into grace, but leaue wee one of the worſt among women, and to returne to one of the beſt among men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſtus</hi> gaue the richeſt and weakeſt kingdoms of the world to the <hi>Senate,</hi> reſeruing the pooreſt and the moſt warlike to himſelfe, by which deuiſe hee kept the <hi>Senate</hi> in a perpetuall honourable bondage. Alſo he made a double Exchequer, the firſt he called his owne, the other the Common-wealths, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that craftie Churle, which hauing two cheſts, the one emptie, which he called all the world, the other full, which hee termed his friend, being reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to lend, would aunſwere he had no coine in all the world, but hee would goe to his friend, who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21132:13"/> would not lend but for intereſt. For indeede <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> vſed both theſe Exchequers as his owne Concubines: likewiſe he appointed triumphall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments for victorious <hi>Senators,</hi> ſtill reſeruing the triumph it ſelfe, for himſelfe, and his ſucceſſors; and ſo played with the Romanes, as vermine doe with poultry, ſucking the beſt blood, and leauing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe for all commers: but what ſhould I ſpeake of all his publike actions and myſteries of ſtate, one priuate policie ſhall be an hoſtage for all; he deſired to haue a bond-man giue teſtimony againſt his maſter, it was anſwered, that it was againſt law, whereupon hee cauſed him to be ſold to another, and ſo made him his accuſer, is not this to call ſtumbling ſtarting, and iadiſh dulneſſe, nothing but forget fulneſſe: true it is that <hi>Tacitus</hi> records this of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> with whoſe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and wilie nature, this ſeemeth to bee very conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but <hi>Dion</hi> ſaith, hee had his plot-forme from <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> it is not improbable, ſeeing he had his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident from him in moſt matters of regiment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THat we may ſomething drawe on this webbe of ſtory, the ſucceeding Romane Emperous, haue throughly declared what Names can doe in policie. Infinite examples are found in <hi>Tiberius,</hi> which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, were to write againe the eleuen firſt bookes of <hi>Tacitus</hi> his Annals, not vnlike <hi>Cryſippus,</hi> who for a<note place="margin">Laertius in vita Cryſippi.</note> citation, writ downe a whole Tragedie of <hi>Euripides:</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21132:13"/> or many moderne bunglers, which are rather <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptores,</hi> then <hi>ſcriptores:</hi> and as it was merily ſaid, bad ſprings of water, but good leaden ſpouts: but to<note place="margin">Gilbert in Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nete.</note> returne to <hi>Tiberius,</hi> it is no maruaile, though <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> report, that <hi>Domitian</hi> only would read the Acts and Records of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> for by that little which <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> hath left, the reſt being conſumed, as it ſeemes by <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> or by ſome timorous Tyrant, it doth appeare that by the changing of Names, and ſhew of libertie, he brought the Romanes vnder the loweſt degree of baſeſt ſeruilitie: hee would not bee called Lord, but played the Vſurper and the Tyrant: he would haue the Empire diuided into three parts, and when he was demaunded which part hee would haue, he aunſwered indeed, that it did not befit his modeſtie to chuſe, but though it were replied, this queſtion was asked to ſhew the indiuiſibilitie of the kingdome, yet he purſued the Author of this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely Gallus to the death. In a word, hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpake as hee thought, and yet hated them moſt that ſeemed but the leaſt to ſuſpect or miſtruſt him, and I am affraid if all <hi>Tacitus</hi> were extant, the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſtate would bee too much expoſed to vulgat eyes, of all which, this is one maine <hi>Maxim,</hi> that the name be as little changed as may bee, though the thing bee altered: the like things are obſerued by <hi>Herodiane</hi> in the liues of <hi>Seuerus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Maximinus:</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Church writers in the liues of <hi>Conſtantine, Iuſtiniane,</hi> and others; but I will not mount too hie, leaſt with <hi>Phaeton</hi> I fall into <hi>Rhodanus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21132:14"/>
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>TO aleage other ſtories, would either be too diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, or at leaſt too laborious, to aleage our own Chronicles, would ſeeme too perilous: but ſome wil ſay, doe you condemne all policie in Names, or Names in policie? To this I frame this direct, but (yet I feare me in regard of ſome) an obſcure anſwer, policie and moralitie as they are ſundry arts, ſo they aime at ſeuerall ends, for policie ſheweth what can be done, moralitie what ſhould be done; the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt ſaith, men ſhould be good and not mutinous, the Polititian anſwereth, that men commonly neither are nor will be good, except they bee conſtrained or deceiued: no conſtraint being violent can be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, but deceit being more ſecret, is more ſecure and durable: when we giue Alloes to children, wee giue it in the pappe of an Apple, that being receiued, they may eate; and eating may liue. So common people many times to their owne good muſt be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, it is not requiſite in a familie, that the ſeruant ſhould know in all points his maſters will; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo long as no euill is commaunded, the ſecrets of ſtate howſoeuer they ſeeme to deceiue the many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed multitude, yet are moſt lawfull, conuenient, neceſſary. Wherefore we diſcommend not <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Domitian;</hi> becauſe they vſed cunning, and many times colluſion; but becauſe they abuſed it, in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying the ſame to murther and luſt. Briefly let no captious Cauiller with ſharper nailes then wit, claw
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21132:14"/> at this poſition: Ethicks and policie are not contrary, but yet diuers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>THis bitter pill wee will once againe lenifie with an other Iulip or a Pozeme, that it may be the more gently intertained: as in all policy, ſo princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in that which is Militarie, error in Names is moſt ſubtile, yet moſt profitable: The three <hi>Decij in Liuie</hi> commanded, if they were killed in the battaile, it ſhould be giuen out, that they did voluntarie run into the midſt of the enemies, vpon a vowe for the ſafetie of the Common-wealth, ſo that their death was not preiudiciall to the armie, as otherwiſe it would haue bene. <hi>Haniball</hi> hauing ouercome the Romanes, put on their armour, and ſo his ſouldiers being taken for Romanes, wonne a City vnder their ſubiection: <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> when his Souldiers muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, onely vſed this word <hi>Quirites,</hi> that is Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Rome, by which they vnderſtood, that hee would casſheare them from their militarie ſeruice, at which word they were ſo aſtoniſhed, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly they deſiſted from ſedition, and with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe in apparance obtained pardon: wee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with later examples, <hi>Scanderbegge</hi> King of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania, when hee felt the pangs of death to approch, commaunded the armie ſhould martch, and withall that it ſhould be proclaimed, that himſelfe was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing forward; which Proclamation did ſo amate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21132:15"/> the Turkes his enemies, that preſently they brake their rankes, without breaking a Lance. <hi>Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> the Emperour of Tartary would not cut his haire after the manner of his owne Country, but ware it long, ſaying, that hee came (by the mothers ſide) from <hi>Sampſon,</hi> whoſe ſtrength was ſuppoſed to conſiſt in his haire, by which fable he obtained this honor, that he was thought inuincible. To conclude, error by names in warlike, and in all other policies, hath bene held to be of leaſt perill and moſt efficacy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VI.</head>
                  <p>BVt ſome will grinne againſt that which hath bin ſaid, that error of Names hath bene the Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtris of learned flatteries, which are the cankers of Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ants, and many times the apoplexies of eſtates, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Suetonius</hi> doe ſhewe in <hi>Nero; Dion,</hi> and <hi>Herodian</hi> declare in <hi>Commodus;</hi> but as I take it, <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the beginning of the life of <hi>Iulius Agricola,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the end thereof, hath throughly diſcuſt this doubt, demonſtrating againſt <hi>Thraſeus, Priſcus,</hi> and <hi>Ruſticus,</hi> that to flatter a Tyrant for a mans owne ſafetie, not with any diſhoneſtie, is a thing of no leſſe prayſe then ſecuritie: for tell me why ſhould a man looſe the ſeruice of his head for the freedome of his tongue: which as it is otherwiſe vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not vnlike to him that preacht to them that robd him, ſo many times it kindleth the rage, ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſuſpitions, and iuſtifieth the pretences of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21132:15"/> whereas a modeſt ſilence would reſerue a man to better times.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII,</hi> All fallacies come by Names.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>HAuing a while waded in the wide Ocean of Policie, which dependeth vpon expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall Reaſon, it reſteth that we treate of Reaſon artificiall, commonly intituled Logicke, which though ſhee be full of Thornes, yet if wee put ouer our hedging Mittens, may bee tractable: we auouch then that all fallacians, which are errors in Logicke, doe iſſue from Names, which like the Rainebow: <hi>Mille trahunt varios aduerſo ſole</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aeneid. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>colores,</hi> and receiue as many formes as <hi>materia prima,</hi> or as <hi>Quartilla</hi> did louers, and this may be thus made perſpicuous. The thirteene fallacians, as they are commonly reckoned, may bee all reduced to <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia Elenchi,</hi> which is when the ſubiect of the Queſtion is taken away, or the ſtate changed, this is plaine by inſtance:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Carmina Paulus emit, recitat ſua Carmina Paulus,<note place="margin">Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iall.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nam quod emit, poſsit dicere quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuum.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paulus</hi> byes Verſes, ſayes th'are his, no lie,</l>
                     <l>For what more right our owne, then that we buy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>In this fallacie of Equiuocation, by the word <hi>ſuum</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21132:16"/> and <hi>ſua,</hi> the ſtate of the queſtion is inuerted, for the Verſes were his by the right of a poſſeſſour, not of a maker. Likewiſe in that Oracle, <hi>Domine mancas hoſtes enim penetrabunt terram tuam, &amp; ſubijcientur domui</hi>
                     <note place="margin">K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>kerman in his third Booke of Logicke.</note> 
                     <hi>tuae,</hi> which indeede ſhould haue beene written thus, <hi>Domi ne maneas, hoſtes enim penetrabunt terram tuam, &amp; ſubijcient</hi> Vr <hi>domui tuae,</hi> Now <hi>Vr</hi> in Chalde ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth fire. In this Oracle, I ſay, wherin are the fallacies of <hi>Amphibole,</hi> Compoſition, Diuiſion, Accent, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of ſpeech: The ſtate of the Queſtion is altered, as appeares by the contrarietie of interpretations the ſame is moſt ocularly manifeſt in the other ſixe fallacies, for that which we call <hi>Polyzeteſis,</hi> or many Interrogations, is nothing but an Equiuocation turn'd into a Queſtion, and ſo is of the ſame nature. Alſo in this Example, <hi>Qui te animal dicit verum praedicat, at qui te aſinum idem &amp; te animal dicit, ergo.</hi> The <hi>Elenchs</hi> of <hi>accidents ſecundum quid,</hi> are lurking, and yet with all the Queſtion is changed, for the reaſon is drawen from a particular to an vniuerſall, which is moſt prepoſterous and retrograde, ſo where the Queſtion is begged, the ſtreame of the diſputati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on turnes his channell: Laſtly, in fallacies of a <hi>Non conſequente &amp; a non cauſa,</hi> there is nothing but a change of the Queſtion, which is in effect but a Name inuerted, not vnlike the legerdemaine of Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or the glittering gloſſe of Alcumiſts gold, which though it ſatisfie the eye, it will hardly indure the ſtampe, the touchſtone, or the hammer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21132:16"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>FVrthermore ſeeing darkneſſe is knowen by light, and deafeneſſe by hearing, fallacies being the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the Soule, are knowen by their ſoueraigne medicines. Now as the Sunne driues away the Wind and the Cloudes, ſo a diſtinction onely doth extinguiſh the <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> and diſpell the miſtie my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of cheating falacies. There are indeede three wayes to diſſolue an Argument, deniall, retorting, and diſtinction, but Deniall is too hoſtile, ſauoring more of obſtinacie then of Arte, retorſion is more wittie then profitable, in a word, Deniall is like ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and launcing, Retorſion like medicines draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or purging, Diſtinction is like to ripening reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or to purges which we call <hi>benedicta,</hi> becauſe they clenſe and feede. Now I would be iudged by a crewe of <hi>Critikes,</hi> neither doe I paſſe though the ſoule of <hi>Lipſius</hi> were coniurde from his Purgatorie, the verdict I craue is vpon this point, whether a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction be any other thing, then the enumeration of ſundry ſignifications of the ſame word, with an apt application to the thing in queſtion. By this it is cleare, that a falacie is like the Sea-prophet <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> to whom if any came to conſult, he would turne himſelfe both into water and fire, both into a ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Tree and a ſauage Tyger, and in fine into euery forme of formes: But if the conſulter did but binde him, not fearing or regarding his ſhapes, then would he yeeld a direct anſwere to his demaund, ſo if you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21132:17"/> bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de a fallacie with the chaines of a diſtinction, you ſhall cauſe her to appeare in her owne likeneſſe, like <hi>Dueſſa</hi> diſroab'd by Prince <hi>Arthur.</hi> In briefe, it is largely confirmed by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> in the fourth Booke of his <hi>Metaphyſickes,</hi> which is commonly called the Booke of Diſtinctions, that all errour proceedeth from indiſtinction of Names, not much vnlike the halucination, or errour of the ſight in the Arte <hi>Opticke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>NEither are fallacies onely impaled within the<note place="margin">Marloe.</note> Schooles, but as farre as <hi>Boreas</hi> claps his braſen wings, and whereſoeuer men or wits be found, there is either the fuell or the fier of deceit: no not in warre where <hi>Thalius</hi> harpe cannot be heard for the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of horſes, no not in religion which is a cloake ſo large, that it may couer the whole world; as <hi>Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlane</hi> was wont to ſay: no not in a mans moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired meditations (where one would be moſt loth to put a tricke vpon himſelfe) will any place bee found ſo narrow, where deceit wil not hatch, if her egges in time be not broken. For as at the dawning of the day, in each part of the aire, darkeneſſe is mingled with light; ſo in euery part of the ſoule, error cleaues faſt to truth. In the Theorick vnderſtanding, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ignorance: In the Practicke, faith and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, prudence and folly: In the Conſcience, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and reſolution: laſtly in the Affections, toward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21132:17"/> and waywardneſſe: and according to the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar opinion, vice and vertue wage warre without truce: and rage like the Sea of Oſeria, which ebbes and flowes foure and twentie times each day: hence we conclude that fallacies are <hi>vbiquitaries,</hi> and buſie as newes-mongers, and that as each part of the body hath ſome diſeaſe ſent from the Witch <hi>Acraſia,</hi> which is intemperance: ſo there is no part or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mans life, which may not bee ouergrowen by the brambles of ſome fallacie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> New Names of Fortitude.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing then this leproſie of errour doeth creep vpon alwals, let vs examine it firſt in vertues, wherin we wil follow the knowen tract, being a thing not ſo hard as imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to mint new diuiſions of vertues: the chiefe vertue then is Fortitude, a mediocritie in deſpiſing dangers, and wee may extend it to be conſtancie, which makes euery vertue a habite: but now all you <hi>Muſes, Heliconides, Aonides, Peonides, Sycilides, Lebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrides,</hi> and if there be any other kindes come to my ayde, for as the Poet ſaith, <hi>Grande loquuturi nebulas</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Perſius. Satyr. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Helicone legunto,</hi> ayde me I pray you, and ſhew mee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21132:18"/> into what ſhapes of Names this Fortitude hath beene tranſelementated. Firſt therefore ſingle fight by many greene heads hath beene ſo well eſteemed, that whoſoeuer doeth refuſe it, is proclaimed a daſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard: we know indeede that <hi>Dauid</hi> by heroycall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, did trie a ſingle combat with <hi>Goliah,</hi> but this is not exemplarie: Againe the Romanes tollerated the combat of the three <hi>Horatii</hi> with the <hi>Curiatii,</hi> but it prooued afterwards preiudiciall to them, neither was it done but in the infancie and barbariſme of their ſtate. Laſtly a Battell for triall of truth, was allowed by the poſitiue Lawes of ſundry Countries, but now they are repealed, as being made in the times of vnciuill ignorance: for what can bee more perilous in Warre, then by the death of one enemie to hope for a compleate victorie, and by the fall of ſome one friend to betray the reſt, as yet vntouched, vnto wilfull ſlauerie: Were it not a ſtrange thing to iudge of ſounds by taſte, no leſſe vncoth is it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne right by a combat: May not the vniuſter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon bee more ſtrong, more skilfull, or at leaſt more ſubtill? but if they anſwere, but yet not more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, let them know they tempt Prouidence, and therefore prouoke her, no maruaile then though the Turkes at this day doe point ſingle Combatants to be burnt in the ſide with hotte coales of fire, theſe ſhall riſe againſt vs in iudgement, when it ſhall bee told vs that this ſingle combat is no Fortitude, but an impatient diſtruſt in the diuine adminiſtration, as if it could not preſent vs with iuſt occaſions of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our valour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21132:18"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THere reignes another humour not vnlike the former, namely reuenges deſire much practiſed in Suites of Law, which ſerue inſtead of Ciuill warres, for whileſt <hi>Bellona</hi> waſteth the Countrey, there is a perpetual vacation in law, but when Peace returneth, the Tearme begins, ſo that men alwayes muſt be waging warre or Law, but of this hereafter: meane time the Spirit of reuenge in generall, hath borrowed the viſard of Fortitude, and yet it is found in all miſhapen, wrinckled, hollow-eyed: In a word, anger flaming witches, for vpon hope of reuenge, only thoſe bloody couenants are commonly drawn with Sathan: the ground of this error is, that men forget that, whereof no man can be ignorant, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Of</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>to worke forcibly,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>a ſteppe.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>to diſtribute.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the reuenging eye, the Heathens had many Names for their Goddeſſe of reuenge, as <hi>Erynnis, Icnaea, Nemeſis, Ramnaſia, Astraea, Ceres,</hi> for all theſe are but one, though ſome reſpects of difference haue bene found in the names, ſhe was termed <hi>Erinnis,</hi> of her violent actions againſt euill men: Likewiſe <hi>Icnaea</hi> becauſe ſhee hunted them as it were by footeſteps: Shee was intituled <hi>Nemeſis</hi> for diſtributing due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, <hi>Ramnuſia</hi> was a particular name giuen by the <hi>Ramnenſes,</hi> which were the followers of <hi>Romulus,</hi> to appeaſe the Ghoſts of <hi>Remus,</hi> which were called at the firſt, <hi>remures,</hi> but afterwards <hi>lemures. Astraea</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid. de Triſt.</note> is not onely the name of Iuſtice, but of reuenge, for Iuſtice many times with Iron hand, though with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21132:19"/> leaden feete, doth reuenge long ſmoothered crimes:<note place="margin">Metamor. 5.</note> Laſtly <hi>Ceres</hi> is brought in plaguing the earth with Cockle, Darnell, barrenneſſe for the loſſe of <hi>Proſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Of</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Murder. a priuatiuum and</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>a bedde.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>enuie.</hi>
                     </note> What ſhould we ſay of <hi>Tyſiphone,</hi> reuenging murther, <hi>Alecto,</hi> vnchaſtitie, <hi>Megaera</hi> ſtrife and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, by all which it appeareth, that the Heathens will condemne vs before the true <hi>Minos,</hi> for our reueng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires, masked with the Name of Fortitude, which is notwithſtanding taken a <hi>Ferendo</hi> not a <hi>feri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo, nam patiendo, male non faciendo, fortes ſumus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe next Cheater vnder the name of Fortitude, is that deſperate reſolution, which is found in Saylers, a thing grounded vpon cuſtome and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, and indeede built vpon the ſand, for not onely in ſtormes, they are found ridiculouſly fearefull, but eſpecially in Sea-fights, the moſt deſperate Sea-men diſcouer their cowardize. This was obſerued in the <hi>Romane gladiatores,</hi> and with vs in our executioners and Bearewards, that though otherwiſe they bee bloody, and obſtinate, yet if they fall into a danger without the compaſſe of their owne element, they are found to be moſt meticulous, for indeede he that deſpiſeth not all dangers equally, deſpiſeth none reſoluedly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21132:19"/>
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>MAns mind is like a diſtempered Locke, which wil neither open nor ſhut, or like a man that by halting in ieſt, is become lame in earneſt: ſtrange it is, that Male-contentment ſhould be now counted the ſtraine of reſolution and badge of Fortitude, neither is this a new error: For why were <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſsius,</hi> and after them <hi>Cato Vticenſis,</hi> ſo much renowmed for their fortitude? Was it not becauſe they were great male-contents. But now not the oppreſſion of our libertie &amp; ruine of our Countrey, hath brought forth this melancholike ſtreames, Idlenes and want of imployment, ioyned with pride and <hi>Epicuriſme,</hi> haue drawne vs into this back ward paſſion, but more of this in Magnanimitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>THere remaineth yet an other order of men, which haue borrowed the <hi>Gregorian</hi> or falſe haire of fortitude, Namely, ſuch as thinke it valour to reſiſt Lawes and Officers, a vertue vnknowen in other Countreyes, where all ſuch reſiſtance is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued with ſeueritie of corporall paine, and infamous in dignitie, but ſuch is our popular indulgence, that we winke at it in all, commend it in ſome: And no maruaile, for we finde the vulgar voice ſo condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Serieants, and other Officers, as if the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:21132:20"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>New Names of Temperance.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Emperance is a kind of Fortitude, in bearing the violent aſſaults of luſt and other appetites: So Fortitude is a kind of Temperance, moderating and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering the turbulent affections, and therefore by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> iuſtly Temperance is marſhald<note place="margin">Ethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 3. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> de arte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> in the ſecond ranke, and by ſome is made the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mediocritie of all vertues. But infinite are the diſtempers of gloſing and ſeeming Temperance, to omit Heretickes and Turkes, the moderne vale of chaſtitie is drawne ouer ſundry Realmes, Adulterie ſeemes to be much condemned, and yet Stewes are
<pb facs="tcp:21132:20"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap> compelled to lie in yron beddes) as the iealous locks wherewith chaſtity is rather tempted then taught, a grieuous error in Names to hold, that harlots are free for their luſt, and wiues muſt neuer be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the contagion of ſuſpition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>AN other kind of Temperance is in drinke and meat, wherein there is a Babiloniſh confuſion of Names: in Italy, and Spaine, wee are condemned for great gluttons, the Germanes for great drinkers, and ſome haue not doubted to anſwere, that it is their nationall ſinne, which is vntrue: for before the Teutones and Tygurines came ouer the Alpes, what time they beſieged the Capitoll of Rome, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21132:21"/> there were no grapes in Germanie; this being the onely true occaſion of that warre; a certaine Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian returning from Rome into Germany, where he was borne, brought with him certaine grapes, at the ſight and teſte whereof, the Germanes deſired to inuade Italy; and therefore drunkenneſſe was not alwayes the nationall ſinne of Germany. Beſides the great Temperance of the old Britons &amp; Saxons, and of ſundry Normane Kings, as <hi>Rufus, Stephen, Henrie</hi> the firſt, ſurnamed <hi>Beauclarke:</hi> doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that our ſurfeting doth not onely proceede from the climate, nor onely from the Petigree, wee being deriued from Saxons, which be Germanes; and Normanes, which came out of France, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from Denmarke: except we ſhould likewiſe imagine ſuſpition is the nationall ſinne of Italy, and pride of Spaine, whereas wee know that vnder the auncient Romanes, Italy was famous for plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and before the Gothes ouerranne Spaine, it was as void of pride as now it is of drunkenneſſe.</p>
                  <p>To determine this matter, theſe things make a ſinne, as it were nationall. Firſt the Petigree, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the Climare, thirdly the Neighbour-borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſome nation, fourthly Impunity, fiftly ſome corruption in Religion, laſtly ouermuch Peace: for example, it cannot bee denied, but that great luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hath ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aken our land, for we came of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes and French, the one a hungry, the other a daintie Nation; and ſo we learne to exceede both in quantitie and qualitie of diet. Againe, our Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate is cold in reſpect of Italy or Spaine, ſo that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21132:21"/> Italian comming into our Countrey, eateth more liberally then at home, the externall cold kindling the heat of the ſtomacke: likewiſe our neighbours are the Low Dutch, much boaſting with <hi>Darius,</hi> that they can beare wine. As for impunitie of luxurie it is very ſtrange, ſeeing it is not onely not puniſht, but euen defended and rewarded: of corruption in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion we ſhall treate hereafter. Laſtly, for long peace, it cannot be denied, but as the hot ſands in Affrica bring forth continually newe Serpents: ſo this daily and nightly produceth newe exceſſiue pleaſures. The ſumme is, Temperance if it be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the ſtomacke of any one Countrey, it ſhall be meted with a Lesbian and mutable rule. So that if we ſtile all Engliſh gluttons, and Germanes drunkards, the ſpeech will ſauor of popularity more then of charity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THere followeth yet a more daungerous error, more affecting or rather infecting our manners, drunkennes of late daies hath found among vs <hi>patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia,</hi> and <hi>matrimonia,</hi> &amp; euery where <hi>patrocinia,</hi> and is maintained with ſome ſhadowes of truth, the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> are ſaid to be drunke, whereas indeede the meaning is, they dranke liberally of the beſt, they<note place="margin">Gene. 43. 34. Compare Hagg 1. 16. Iohn 2. 10.</note> drunke the cup of neceſſitie, ſtrength, delight, and it may be of ſleepe: but who touched the cup of folly, of luſt, of furie: with no leſſe infelicitie doe they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21132:22"/> rather then produce <hi>Salomon,</hi> hee bids thee<note place="margin">Prou. 31. 6.</note> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inke that thou mayeſt bee glad for a ſeaſon, not void of reaſon with vntimely madneſſe: wee haue heard ſay, that the Danes thinke, what entereth in,<note place="margin">Matth. 15. 20.</note> defileth not, but what they vomite. If this be true, I am ſure they vomite great blaſphemies, for in that place is mention of ſuch things onely, which iſſue from the heart and ſoule, not from the ſtomach: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue found drunkenneſſe to bee a remedie for a quartan, and haue purchaſt withall an habite of drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. So that of ſicke men, they are become ſound beaſts: other defences as of company, of gentry, of inforcement, and the like are confuted by the bare repeating. To conclude, it is ſhame that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations of drinking are not diſſolued by ſeuerer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of good lawes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> New Names of Liberalitie and Magnificence.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Iberalitv and Magnificence, differs as a Pike and a Pikerell, the former being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant about ordinary beneuolence; the latter about ſumptuous workes, but as I take it, this diſtinction is not ſo much found in the thing, as in the flattery of writers; the firſt Gangren of this vertue, is the falſe name of hoſpitalitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21132:22"/> by men fill the full onely, maintaining either Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of recreation, otherwiſe lawfull: as Horſe, Hauke, Hound; or of meere pompe, as multitude of ſeruants without office, or of importunacy, as vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Vagrants, or of mutuall flatterie, as men that can re-inuite them: meane while, the labouring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potent, the ſicke, the impriſoned, the neceſſarily wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring; the learned and miniſteriall poore are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. The Names of Lord and Ladie, as is proued out of the Saxon recordes, were giuen in auncient<note place="margin">Verſtegands Antiquities.</note> time, for true hoſpitality: for Lord was written <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> now <hi>Lafh</hi> is that which we call loafe, but ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth bread in generall: not the forme onely. Hee therefore was a <hi>La-forde,</hi> or a Lord, that afforded bread: this terme Ladie was written <hi>Laphdian,</hi> that is a woman, diuiding or diſtributing Bread allowed by her Lord and husband: The name remaines, the thing is aboliſht, for either houſekeeping is neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or the rich onely feaſted. Thus did not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes, nor the Grecians, and Romanes, ſo famous for Hoſpitalitie, other Nations greatly contemne vs, though with a greater pride bending on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide to couetous ſolitarineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>AN other poyſon of pretended liberalitie, is the Phrenſie of building, a thing well Painted by many, but yet in the end it prooueth a rotten poſte. The Bricklayers of Babel, and the Kings of Egypt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21132:23"/> that made the Pyramides by the labour of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lites, doe partly ſhew vs, what bad ſucceſſe theſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles did purchaſe: the manifold terrors of <hi>Caine,</hi> the builder of the firſt Citie; the curſe of him that built Iericho, the madneſſe of <hi>Nabuchadonoſer,</hi> who built Babel for his owne glorie, doe teſtifie<note place="margin">Lycanthropia, a diſeaſe wherein men thinke themſelues to be beaſts.</note> ſometimes the ruine, often the infelicitie, alwayes the vanitie of the dooers. To conclude this, let buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders remember that to be moſt true, that <hi>Ouid</hi> ſpake in an other ſenſe.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Eſſe quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in fatis reminiſcitur affore tempus;</l>
                     <l>Quo mare, quo tellus, correpta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> regia Caeli<note place="margin">Metamor. 1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ardeat, &amp; mundi moles operoſa laboret.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>It was but a fable of <hi>Phaeton,</hi> but we expect now that it ſhall bee both truely and ſhortly perform'de, at what time theſe buildings will make a faire ſhow in the publike fire, as <hi>Nero</hi> ſaid of Rome, when it was a burning. As for the Almes which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in building, they are like the white of an Egge without ſalt, for the labourer is worthy of his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, neither can Almes and ſtipend concurre in the ſame Salarie or gift.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third Impoſture is, our Engliſh Apiſh vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whereby wee tire our ſelues in changes of ſtrange coſtly and gaudie tyre, not to couer naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not for ornament and diſtinction of orders,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21132:23"/> not for defence alone, but to ſhew our leuitie in imitation, our facilitie in aluring, beſide our need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe expenſe and lunaſicke inconſtancie. So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſundry Diſeaſes are ſent from other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to vs: Yet we are alwayes the cauſe of the Chin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cough<note place="margin">Cachinnus.</note> in other Countreyes, whileſt they wonder at vs, which as a King-<hi>Fiſher</hi> being dead, change with the wind, that is with each faſhion, not vnlike Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſicke of the faſhions; Indeede other Countreyes retaine their old habit, out of pride contemning the in frugalitie of new inuentions, but we are changed with ſordid mutabilitie, aſcribing the fault com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to Women or Taylors, who ſerue like Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes or Dogges among Ladies, vpon the ſent of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill ſauors: Whereas the truth is, the husbands pride like the luſter of the Sunne, is ſeene in his wife repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Raine-bow. When <hi>Solon</hi> came before <hi>Creſus,</hi> being demaunded, whether hee had ſeene a more pompous ſhow, anſwered hee had ſeene Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants and Peacockes in their natiue habit, as for his apparell it was borrowed. O <hi>Solon,</hi> hadſt thou knowne how raiment came vp, thou ſhouldeſt haue ſeene that thou ſpakeſt not by gueſſe: It was ſaid, <hi>Is not the body more worth then rayment?</hi> as if the body without rayment might be ſafe, for not onely in the Golden age before <hi>Adams</hi> fall, was there no neede of ſuch borrowed veſture, but euen in this Iron ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherein Gold is of moſt eſtimation. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage Indians, rather vpon ignorance of vice, then affection to vertue, keepe all parts bare, ſaue thoſe which nature biddes ſhould bee concealde, their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21132:24"/> ſimplicitie, being a ragged remnant of our ruined innocencie: And if the temperament of our Climate would indure the ſame, we doubt not but the bodies of ſober minds would admit the like naked ſinceritie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THe fourth coloured name of Magnificence, is<note place="margin">Dion in Claudio.</note> painting, a notable preſident wherof was <hi>Poppaea,</hi> which had the Milke of fiue hundreth ſhee Aſſes to waſh her face with, the oldeſt patterne we reade of, was <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> though ſome would fetch it farther from<note place="margin">Iob 42.</note> 
                     <hi>Iobs</hi> daughter, which was named <hi>Cheren-happucke,</hi> by interpretation the horne of <hi>ſtibium</hi> or complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but I thinke if ſome noſe-wiſe <hi>Criticke</hi> were here<note place="margin">Nice No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> de.</note> he would think that ſhe was ſo called for her natural beauty, exceeding all Painting, but it is not ſafe of an <hi>Etimologie</hi> to make an Hiſtorie, except we like his Dreame, that ſaid <hi>Brutus</hi> was an adulterer, becauſe<note place="margin">O Brutus for Obrutus.</note> of ſelfe-will, he thus read <hi>Ouids</hi> verſe, <hi>O</hi> Brutus <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanis eſſet adulter aquis,</hi> whereas tis certaine that <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> reuenged the Rape of <hi>Lucreſe,</hi> and the Adulterie of <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> but ſuch lippes ſuch lettiſſe, Painted ſtories &amp; Painted faces may well agree, the latter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made to offend by inchantments, the former to defend them, certaine it is that as <hi>Gunnes</hi> haue taken away manhood, ſo Painting hath diſgra'ſt beautie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21132:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Magnanimitis and Modestie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next golden paire of vertues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reputed, are Magnanimitie and Modeſtie, differing in qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>titie as the former vertues, the firſt being ſeene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout great Honours, the ſecond about ſmaller, theſe diſtinctions we will not now refute, leaſt wee ſhould ſeeme <hi>Parentes colere,</hi> that is to plough vp our Fathers graues, as it was ſaid by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus.</hi> The firſt <hi>Cantherist</hi> that eates vp the rootes of this tree, is ſelfe-loue, which men (who skilfull to ſucke Milke out of a Flint) haue thus aſſayed to draw out of the fountaine of veritie, it is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> And therefore ſelfe-loue is enioyned, for the rule is better then the thing ruled, but ſelfe-loue is the rule. The thing ruled is the loue of the neighbour, ſelfe-loue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is better and more inioyn'd. We anſwere, that Loue of our ſelues, is a rule naturall not morall, like as when we ſay, be Morally dilligent, as the Piſmire is naturally, Alſo loue thy neighbour Morally, as Chriſt hath loued thee ſupernaturally: For tell me, thou that iudgeſt without preiudice, when it is ſaid, <hi>Loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> is this thy meaning, as thou doſt, or as thou oughteſt to loue thy ſelfe? The
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21132:25"/> firſt being in nature, the latter in duetie, if thou auer the latter as ſome haue done, then tell mee how ought I to loue my ſelfe? Is not now the rule as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine as the thing ruled, and hath euer any man<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> offended in this duetie, hath euer any hated his owne fleſh, is not this vertue found in bruite beaſts aſwell as men? Nay, can we thinke the Prince of darkeneſſe loueth not himſelfe. To conclude, where it is ſaid, I hate them as if they were mine enemies, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, I hate them as, if I were a naturall man, I ſhould hate my naturall foes, ſo when it is ſaid, <hi>Loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe,</hi> this is the meaning; That which by nature thou doſt to thy ſelfe, by duetie performe to thy brother.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>BY this it is plaine, that the Name of Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie being defined to bee a vertue, whereby a man being worthy of great honour, thinks himſelfe worthy of the ſame, doeth ſomething ſmell of the Brimſtone of heatheniſh pride, for of what honour ſhould a man dreame himſelfe to be worthy, ſeeing the higheſt top of all knowledge, is to acknowledge that we haue none, and the faireſt buildings of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſhould be laide vpon the foundation of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Tis ſaid that <hi>Neptune</hi> did helpe to build the Walles of Troy, becauſe in the foundation of building, we ſhould digge till we come where there is water. Humilitie then the foundation of Vertue,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21132:25"/> muſt be laid vpon the water of contrition, iſſuing from the cleere fountaine, wherein we ſee the faces of our owne miſery: and therefore ſome haue not doubted to ſay, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the great praiſes of magnanimity, did ſowe pillowes vnder <hi>Alexanders</hi> elbowes: other deny the booke of Ethicks to be his, becauſe <hi>Nichomacus</hi> (as they ſay) was but ſixe yeere old when he died, as if <hi>Quintilian</hi> did not dedicate his inſtitutions to his ſonne at the ſame yeeres, other ſay, that theſe Ethicall diſcourſes were popular, not accurate, but why doe theſe ſillie Hares thus inſult vpon a dead Lyon? I beleeue that he which groped ſo well in the darke, had he ſeene our light, he would haue looked vpon the gliſtering ſunne, aſwell as any of our Eagles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>ANother Moth that frets the Name of Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, is an act, which ſome aſcribe to Fortitude; namely killing of a mans ſelfe, but for as much as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath bene moſt pretended to be ſought by it, it may ſeeme to be a ſtraine of Magnanimity, rather then of Fortitude: now although it hath bene pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, by men otherwiſe famous, yea by women of the nobleſt ſpirits, yet we ſhall find firſt that the fiue examples in Scripture: <hi>Abimelech, Saul,</hi> and his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor-bearer, <hi>Achitophell,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> are branded ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with pride, or with diſpaire: next it is cleere, that <hi>Codrus, Curſius, Minutius,</hi> and others haue done
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21132:26"/> it vpon barbarous ſuperſtition. For Sathan know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſts blood ſhould be the propitiation for the ſinnes of the world, of which the Sacrifices in the law were types, perſwaded the wandring Heathen, that the Diuinity was onely appeaſed by humane blood, hence wee haue the oblations to <hi>Molech</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ammonites, and to <hi>Saturne</hi> among the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Looke</hi> Tobie Matthew <hi>his Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before the Queene, 1580.</hi>
                     </note> Carthaginians, Thraſians and Samnites, and to <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> among the Gaules: as for the three <hi>Decij,</hi> I take it, it was no vow but a policie. <hi>Cato Vticenſis</hi> indeed is much praiſed, but I ſuppoſe (all things conſidered) it was but a male contented pride, that droue him to this exigent: as for the women, <hi>Dido, Siſigambis Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Cleopatra,</hi> and others, they are the leſſe to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, becauſe of the great infirmity of their ſexe, and impotencie of their paſſion, and this is much more euident in Martyrs and Virgins, who pretending to ſaue their faith and virginitie, caſt not their wares out of the ſhip, but themſelues out of the world. Their good intent is not to be concealed, their frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be pitied: in briefe it is not lawfull to breake priſon, or to leaue the watch before the appointed hower, and though many glorious yuie buſhes bee hanged ouer this act, yet indeed it is a wine running out of the veſſell of puſillanimitie, neither did any euer kill himſelfe, that dreaded not a daunger greater in ſhew, which thereby he indeuored to eſcape.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21132:26"/>
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>NEither hath only Magnanimitie bene thus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, but Modeſtie hath borrowed many fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one greateſt &amp; moſt deformed ſhe tooke from the laſie Owle, vnder this pretence <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>bene qui</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>latuit, bene vixit, quia latere eſt viuere, &amp; viuere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere:</hi> this nation of men leaneth vpon this principle, a man is borne for himſelfe, and therefore it is but ambition to ſtriue to helpe others, but as the roote is bitter, ſo is the fruit, as the principle is erroneous, ſo is the concluſion; God the Father gaue his whole being to his Sonne, theſe both in vnſpeakeable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner breathed forth the holy Ghoſt; theſe three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons made the world: &amp; rule it with continually-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king aſſiſtance: the Angels are for our ſake ſent out daily vpon certaine myſteries and Miniſteries: <hi>Eue</hi> was made to helpe man, and he to rule both her and all other viſible creatures, the heauens by their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">Scalig. exercita. 300. Sect. 59. 13</note> guide the Elements, which feede the plants, the foode of beaſts, and they of vs: is any part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made for it ſelfe, doth not the liuer miniſter ſpirits to the heart, the heart to the braine, the braine to the whole <hi>microcoſme:</hi> wherefore he that liues to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, quencheth the ſpirit in himſelfe, and burieth his talent, but I ſpare to ſpeake of this any further in this bold and ambitious age, yet many wee know there be, that haue thus erred on the right hand.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21132:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> New Names of Clemencie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeuenth vertue called Clemencie, oppoſed to Crueltie and Indulgence, is aſſaulted by many errors of Names: The firſt is this, ſome thinke, we ought to forgiue all iniuries, not onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of malice, but euen in regard of puniſhment in cenſure: theſe conſider not that prudence is the forme and ſquare of all vertues &amp; ſo of charitie: true it is ſhe ſuffereth all things: namely, which prudence aduiſeth may be ſuffered. Notwithſtanding, firſt it is as true, that to yeeld impunity to euill doers, is in a ſort as dangerous as to puniſh the iuſt. Secondly it is meere follie to aſcribe integritie to an euill man, or to write him in the bead-roule of my friends, that is a cloſe and dangerous enemie: for example to truſt a man of an other Religion, or contrarie faction, vpon what proteſtation or bond ſoeuer, is neerer to phrenzie, then to charitie: credulitie is after a ſort as bad as ſuſpition, for he that beleeues the beſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, holds the truth of no man, for ordinarily it appeareth that men credulous, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the good ſpeaking againſt the bad, and the bad againſt the good, are found in euent, if not in effect moſt ſuſpitious: for as an anarchy and tyranny differ
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21132:27"/> litle, ſo is it like perillous to beleeue all or none. True it is, if a man repent, our cenſure muſt be altered, but our cenſure muſt leane vpon probable Arguments of a mindepenitent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>AN other ſuppoſed enemy of clemencie, is going to Warre and to Law: Againſt Warre, many phanaticall humours haue beene found to rayle; but beſides the ancient teſtimonies and examples, of <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Ioſuah, Dauid,</hi> and others: The<note place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a. 17. 15.</note> New Teſtament deſcribeth the Warre of the tenne Kings as moſt lawfull: Beſides it is manifeſt, if ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects being witches and murtherers, may bee put to death, why may not forraine Princes vpon open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie be repelled, or reclaim'de by Warre: Yea ſay they, but vnder the <hi>Meſsias</hi> they ſhall turne their Swords to Sithes, and Speares to Mattockes, and ſhal learne to fight no more. The meaning is, they ſhall ſurceaſe all Ciuill and inteſtine Warre, they ſhall haue no tumult in conſcience, and in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iudgement all warlike and domeſticall ſtrife ſhall be aboliſht.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe vſe of going to Law, may no leſſe be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo that the cauſe be both true and great, ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21132:28"/> that by no arbitrement, the ſtrife can be determined, ſo that rigour be not ſhewed in the aduantage. True it is, that ſuites before Heathen Iudges were ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ſpecially when the matters might haue beene comprimiſed by priuate Vmpires. But Chriſtian Iudges, and cauſes otherwiſe irreconcileable, remoue this ſtumbling blocke: Alwayes being remembred that fraud, violence, and auarice, creepe not into them that ſhould be patterns and patrons of Iuſtice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>A New <hi>Chymaera</hi> doeth appeare of clemencie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Title of the prerogatiue Royall, when wilfull murtherers, Witches, Sodomites, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Traytors are pardoned, wherein although Princes in the moſt part doe erre, by ignorance of the fact, not of right: Yet <hi>Trapezuntian</hi> flatterers make their Apologies, as if it were lawfull for them to diſpence with any ſinne, not remembring that Kings being Gods vicegerents, may not ſlacke the bridle of his ſeueritie, whom they repreſent. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Suetonius in Domitian.</note> ſaid truely, hee that puniſheth not Informers, cheriſheth them: So he that cutteth not off Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, is acceſſarie for all his Prerogatiue, neither doe we ſhorten the power thereof, but direct the limits. God is ſaid, not to be able to doe that he will not, ſo we may ſay, Princes can not do that they ſhould not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21132:28"/>
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>THe like deceit, but farre more generall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, is Indulgence, whether of Captaines to their Souldiers, or of Parents to their Children. The former being the ruine of Armies, the latter of Families, which as they are the Seminaries of the Common-wealth, ſo they ſpred their defects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all poſſible meanes of redreſſe: Firſt, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Warre; it hath beene found, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious crueltie of <hi>Lucullus</hi> was dangerous to him, as <hi>Appian</hi> ſheweth in the Ciuill Warres, and yet the remiſneſſe of <hi>Scipio</hi> did bring no leſſe damage for a time, till being better informed, he reformed his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Scipio</hi> the yonger, for his prudent ſeueritie before <hi>Numantia,</hi> wherein hee had more adoe with<note place="margin">Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ophon in the expedition of the Graetians.</note> his Souldiers then his enemies, was in a maner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all but <hi>Caeſar. Clearchus</hi> ſaid, a Souldier ſhould feare his Captaine more then his foe. As for the indulgence of Parents, although men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt famous as <hi>Iacob, Ely, Dauid,</hi> haue beene noted for it, yet their infamie and puniſhment, and with all the praiſe of <hi>Abraham, Iudah, Moſes,</hi> in Scripture, and in other ſtories of <hi>Brutus, Manlius, Augustus,</hi> doe ſhew both the rareneſſe of the vertue, and of the vertuous in this behalfe. For men being tainted with a naturall ſelfe-loue, can hardly by reflection, ſee their own faults in their Children, being portions extracted from their ſeede, and moſt times from their follies, ſo that next to the taming
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21132:29"/> of a mans ſelfe-loue, vaine pitie to Children is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt to be ſubdued.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the New Names of Veracitie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>VEracitie a vertue in telling veritie, is Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſhadows of ſundry Names. Firſt, Equiuocation deſires to bee couſen Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine to it, ſaying that it reſerues a lawfull conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as when the magiſtrate demaundeth a thing to the hurt of the partie demanded: for (ſay they) it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ciuill law, &amp; ciuilitie, that a man ſhould accuſe himſelfe: wherein theſe men conſider not they abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>ius ex officio,</hi> a thing by them more practiſed then<note place="margin">Being Papiſts.</note> by vs. Againe, when Chriſt was adiured to tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were the Chriſt; he gaue a teſtimony with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all mentall reſeruation. Now whereas they talke of mixt propoſitions, partly mentall, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vocall, as they diſturbe all ſocieties with their new inuentions: ſo they make their ſpeech a <hi>Centaure,</hi> halfe a man halfe a horſe, or like one of the broodes of Nilus, halfe earth, halfe frog; a thing both ſhape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and ſhaped in one mixture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21132:29"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>A Second baſtard of Veracitiy, is an officious lie, a thing excuſed, defended, and prayſed by many: but if this Lie be ſifted it will be found, that it comes <hi>Ab officio, verbo, non nomine,</hi> That is from hurting, not from helping, for though it bewrayeth not thy friend, yet it betrayeth the trueth, which ſhould be dearer then all friends, in deſence of it many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples haue beene alleadged. <hi>Abraham</hi> lied to ſaue his life, in calling his wife his ſiſter, but I wonder what foreheads theſe men haue, ſeeing <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe auouched that ſhee was his ſiſter by the fathers ſide, beſides this terme ſiſter in that language, importeth euery kinſwoman: Yea, but ſay they, the Midwiues lied, in ſaying the Ebrew women were liuely, and yet God built them Houſes, we anſwere. Firſt, the word liuely may ſignifie Midwiues: Againe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> tongue.</note> women being premoniſhed of the daunger, might by the aide of neighbours without thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Midwiues be deliuered, as the <hi>Vigine Marie</hi> was in Bethelem, and harlots with vs, and all in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica: Now where it is ſaid, God built them Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                              <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>not</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> it is meant of the Iſraelites, not of the Midwiues, the Ebrew word being of the Maſculine gender. Laſtly, though it were meant of the Midwiues, the bleſſing was not granted for their Lie, but for their feare of God, as for the examples of <hi>Iacob, Rahab,</hi> and others, they are no more preſidents to vs, then <hi>Dauids</hi> adulterie, <hi>Salomons</hi> idolatrie, <hi>Peters</hi> Apoſtacie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21132:30"/>
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> II.</note>
                  <p>THe laſt enemy of Veracitie, vnder the title of a prepoſterous name, is a perſeuerance in the truth without auoydance of perſecution: true it is, we may not flie vpon diſtruſt, or againſt conſcience, calling, or charity, otherwiſe we may aſwell flie from purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enemies, as from the foure great plagues, wilde beaſts, peſtilence, famine, warre. Shall we not ſay, that he ſuffereth, who leaueth his Countrey, his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, his goods, rather then hee will howle with Woolues: what if ſome Martyrs haue beene in this error, we liue by lawes, not by examples; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, he that flieth may fight againe as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſaid, and as <hi>Leonidas</hi> Souldiers, may reſerue himſelfe to better times.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> New Names of Comitie and Vrbanitie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ffabilitie or Comitie is a curteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour to all men, Vrbanitie is a pleaſant facility in harmeleſſe ieſts, the firſt error of Name, which ouerſhadoweth Comity is that, which indeed ſhould be termed ambitious flatterie: This firſt is found in men that ſeeke for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21132:30"/> witneſſes be <hi>Iugurtha, Iulius Caeſar, Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the Emperour, In Scripture we haue <hi>Abſolon, Adoniah, Iſmael,</hi> their ends were confuſion, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion was their meanes: now if the fountaine bee<note place="margin">Not be in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, but in J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> poyſoned, what ſhall we thinke of the riuer, it is not lawfull to ſay, that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler forgot <hi>Ioſeph</hi> two yeeres, it is not expedient to ſay, that they can flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that ſee the face of <hi>Ahazzuerus,</hi> they are ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, receiue ſo little benefite by colluſion, and haue ſo ſmall occaſion to vſe it, that a man would little think, that Crowes ſhould build their neaſt ſo neere the palace: true it is that <hi>Solon</hi> ſayd to <hi>Aeſope,</hi> men may not come to <hi>Craeſus</hi> if they will not flatter, but ſure I am when <hi>Craeſus</hi> was tyed to the ſtake to bee burned, he was in another mind, certainly <hi>Aeſope</hi> whither of purpoſe I know not, ſayd, the Lion could not be healed without the Apes liuer, that is, Princes<note place="margin">Herodotus in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o.</note> cannot be ſafe without the death of flatterers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>VRbanity a moſt pleaſant vertue, is peſtered with the affinity of common ieaſting, which vſually hath one of theſe foure vices: firſt, prophaneneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, whoſe name when <hi>Pilate</hi> heard, he trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: ſecondly, biting ſcurrility, whereby men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looſe their gueſt then their ieaſt. <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once troubled at his table with ſuch a Bufphoon, willed him to ieaſt no more at his friends, but at himſelfe: which as <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports was preſently<note place="margin">Suctonius in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſpaſian.</note>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21132:31"/> done in moſt obſcene manner; the third vice then is obcenity: theſe three are in the quality; the laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is in quantity, namely, vnceſſant babling: he that would make a great fire continually, muſt rake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much meane fuell, and he that will alwayes be ſhaking the ſplene of others, muſt haue much curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, more wordes, and moſt lies, his face muſt be as hard as the ſhell of a Tortis, his tongue as ſharpe as the quilles of a Porcupine, his heart as vncleane as the ſtable of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>geus,</hi> before <hi>Hercules</hi> brought in the riuer Alphaeus to clenſe it, and therefore this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dide generation ſhould be baniſht into Affrica, as <hi>Titus</hi> did Promoters.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe abuſe of ſundry Theaters here ſeemes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelfe, which were they reduced to their firſt inſtitution, might heale as much as they now hurt: Among the Romans no womans part was plaid by a man: this was the miſchiefe, the women were Curtiſans; neither indeed can it fit matron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like modeſty to be Actreſſe on a Stage; but by this we conceiue, the heathens ſaw light though through a narrow grate, and if we marke the ancient Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>AEſculus, Sophocles, Seneca,</hi> we ſhall finde the reproofe of <hi>AEſculus,</hi> wherewith he reprooued <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides,</hi> for bringing a woman in loue vpon the ſtage, &amp; for effeminating the mind of the Athenians to haue been moſt iuſt, and yet ſuch is mans frailety,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21132:31"/> he that bringes in this reproouer, doth euery where<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> abound with obſcaenity; I grant it is not ſo comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call as Satyricall, but luſt is ſuch a ſinne as it can hardly be reprehended without ſinne, and hee that will rebuke it, muſt be firſt wicked by experience, or by imitation: no maruell then though all Hiſtrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall perſons were infamous by the Romane law, though they changed no apparrell of their ſexe, though they played but once, and that without hier; though their part had neither dicacitie nor filthines: For prophane ſpeeches were in thoſe dayes capitall, the Cynicks iudgement alſo is to be obſerued, whoſe opinion being demanded of Players, anſwered, the better, the worſe, that is the better Players, the worſe men; and certainely, the Actors are many times<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> more culpaple then the Spectators, ſpecially if their Action be continuall and mercenarie; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, if we marke how young men ſpend the latter end of the day in gaming, drinking, whoring, it were better to tollerate Playes with <hi>Auguſtus, Veſpaſian, Titus, Nerua, Traian,</hi> and other good Emperours, then with <hi>Domitian</hi> to cut downe the vines, leaſt til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage be neglected, remembring the verſes ſet downe by <hi>Suetonius</hi> againſt him:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Rode Caper vitem, tamen hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um ſtabis ad Aras,</l>
                     <l>In tua quod ſpargi Cornua poſsit erit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Well gray-beard, croppe the Vine, yet when thou ſtandſt forlorne</l>
                     <l>At th' alter ſhall be wine to ſprinckle on thy horne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>For it is a Principle in Policie, that the deteining of the multitude by publike ſpectacles, is a great obſtacle to many baſe and clandeſtine Actions,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21132:32"/> and therefore a Player being condemned by <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> for a quarrell at the Theater, anſwered, if theſe things be winked at, the people ſhall haue leſſe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to inquire into your great actions. It is ſaid of<note place="margin">See T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on in his life.</note> the Mantinians in <hi>Polibius,</hi> that the leauing of their Country Muſicke, was the cauſe why they degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Barbariſme and cruelty: ſo I feare if all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſports were reſtrained, our Country would ſoone turne to ſottiſhneſſe or mutineys.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>AN other occaſion of mirth, but hinderance of Vrbanity, is a certaine ſport in cruelty, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon men or beaſts: firſt for men, wee know that among the Romanes whilſt Paganiſme indured, ſword fight was publikely tollerated, whereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in one day ten thouſand were killed; this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh or brutiſh play was aboliſht by decrees of Chriſtian Emperors, not much vnlike this, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which we commonly take in innocents, which were kept in auncient time by great men, partly for ſpectacles of horror and humility; partly for chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and therfore we haue an old ceremonious ſpeech in our Countrey, he cannot but thriue, that keepes a foole, it may be alſo there was a reſpect had to their ability and willingnes to labor, but that men ſhould make ſport vpon their folly, which are no more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to it, then our ſelues: is an argument of ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and vnnaturall crueltie, neither may we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21132:32"/> the immoderate delights in bayting of beaſts and Cock-fights, ſeeing all theſe contentions came by mans fall, ſo that if by accident we behold them, we are thence to draw occaſion of repentance rather then of delight, neither yet may we for all that hence inferre the condemnation of hunting and hawking, the former being allowed by <hi>Iſack</hi> in his eldeſt ſonne, and both of them being but inſtruments of taking thoſe creatures, to which wee haue right: and therefore the accidentall ſport being ſeaſonably taken by men of ability cannot be diſallowed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> New Names of Iuſtice.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vſtice a vertue of giuing euery man his owne, either Arithmetically by diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Geometrically by commutation and compenſation, hath receiued many<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Iuſtin <hi>in the beginning of his firſt Booke.</hi>
                     </note> variable Names: firſt by tyrannicall power of doing all things at the will of a Monarch, without poſitiue lawes in the Countrey, was a long time held for Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; this afterward prooued very preiudiciall, not onely becauſe tyrants made ſtawking horſes of their willes: for it is perilous when men can doe what they will, and will not what they ſhould: but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there did ſucceed many Princes either natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21132:33"/> or by education very defectiue, as <hi>Kilparicke. Charles</hi> the ſimple &amp; others, by whoſe arbitrement, if things had beene moderated and not by Lawes, the Common-wealth muſt haue ſuffred ſhipwrack. Lawes therefore were inuented, and with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie perfected, that the actions both of Tyrants might be repealed &amp; of fooles moderated, Example<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> of which we finde in <hi>Caligula, Commodus,</hi> and <hi>Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantoninus.</hi> The ſame is to be ſeene at this day in the Gouernement of the Turkes, <hi>Preter-Iane,</hi> the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an, and the Ruſſian, in whoſe abſolute Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Lawes are ſilent, equitie being deſtroyed by the rigour of Iuſtice, and this is ſuppoſed to bee the cauſe, why more excellent men haue beene found in free States, as Rome, Athens, Sparta, then in abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Kingdomes, becauſe in them the great Pike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours the Eeles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>BVt although Lawes haue beene moſt needefull, yet three great defects haue bene found in them, Firſt the ſwarming of Suiters, for as many Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in a Citie, argue much intemperance, ſo many Pleaders, much wealth, more hatred, moſt conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Poyſon in phyſicke is an extreame remedie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one deleterious poyſon is hardly tempred but by one of equal ſtrength: law and war are deſperate<note place="margin">Tacitus in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iting of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſius.</note> medicines, and therefore as Informers were much complained on in Rome in the dayes of <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21132:33"/> not becauſe they were ſimply to be taken away, but rather to be diminiſhed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> regard of their number and power, and corrected in reſpect of their fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent malice, learned fraud, and dangerous learning, ſo the ouerflow of ſuites and pleaders, and the ranck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of iniuries in this kind is rather to be lamented then helped, for though the latter be better, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is poſſible: now wee ought to frame our wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes according to poſſibility of thinges, which were it well obſerued, it would bee a cordiall to many,<note place="margin">Epictetus in his Enchry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on.</note> whoſe melancholy, not the land of <hi>Helibore,</hi> no not <hi>Virginia</hi> now can purge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>A Second impotencie is in the execution of laws, when they that might bee moſt operatiue Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, are too much imployed otherwiſe in warre or pleaſure, the Romane Emperours therefore eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the beſt, did often perſonally aſſiſt the iudgement ſeat, yea <hi>Claudius</hi> himſelfe, though otherwiſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by women and ſeruants, yet was much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for a iudgement he pronounced: a certaine widdow hating her owne onely ſonne, defrauded him of his inheritance, ſaying hee was a foundling<note place="margin">A child found and brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> by her hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d.</note> not her ſonne, the young man replyed, that hee was her ſonne, and claimed the land: <hi>Claudius</hi> hereupon commanded the widdow to marry this young man: but ſhee whether through horror of inceſt, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of his perſon, confeſſed that he was her ſonne,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21132:34"/> and ſo the land was adiudged to him, and therefore<note place="margin">The reſurrection of fooles.</note> it may be that thoſe bookes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caes Cotakuntoſis</hi> were made vpon flatterie againſt him, not vpon truth: <hi>Luther</hi> in his booke <hi>de ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miore potentia,</hi> ſheweth how a wiſe Prince is better then all lawes, by a notable example, which was this, one tooke a Noble man priſoner, whoſe wife came to entreate for her husbands life, he anſwered, if ſhe would conſent to his folly, he ſhould be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhe craued firſt licence to conferre with her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band about it, which was granted; her husband al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo gaue her licence to doe it, the next day her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes head being chopt off, was ſent vnto her, whereupon ſhee complained vnto the Duke of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy, who ſending for him, compelled him firſt to marry her, and then beheaded him, intituling her into his lands and goods: this Act hee preferreth before a hundreth ſentences of wreſted law: in briefe, thoſe ſtates are moſt happy, where the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Magiſtrate doth moderate lawes, otherwiſe vnchangeable, as thoſe of the Medes and Perſians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THe third vnhappineſſe of lawes, is when they are not made altogether in the firſt foundation, therefore the common wealthes of Iſrael, Crete, Cybaris, Sparta, Carthage, whoſe lawes were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformely made at once by <hi>Moſes</hi> from God, by <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Charondas, Lycurgus,</hi> and <hi>Phaleas,</hi> are preferred
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21132:34"/> before thoſe kingdomes, whoſe lawes haue been fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſucceſſiuely vpon new occaſions, for we ſee no Romane lawes made in the time of a free eſtate, but vpon ſeditious compulſion, which howſoeuer by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, did inlarge their power, becauſe their muti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies were ended by law, not by ſword: yet if wee marke the ſequell, we ſhall finde, that firſt it was not durable but in warre, being elſe moleſted with<note place="margin">Reade the Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiae hiſtory.</note> ciuill broiles: ſecondly, when it had aſcended to the height, it could not be preſerued without a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy: thirdly, when the Empire was eſtabliſht, it was<note place="margin">See Dion in Auguſtus.</note> like neuer long to endure, as both the euent decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and by narration of the cauſes, might eaſily bee conuinced. To conclude, happie bee the countries, whoſe lawes are framed with the caution made by <hi>Carondas,</hi> who did ordaine, if any man would change<note place="margin">Dio lorus Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liotheca.</note> a law made, hee ſhould come wearing a rope about his necke, with which he ſhould be executed, if his new inuention were not found better then the olde conſtitution: were this performed, interpretation and execution of olde lawes would ſerue without innouation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>DIuers things are pretended to be enemies to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as firſt the remitting of the rigor of our auncient lawes, whereby wilfull murtherers were hanged aliue in chaines; but howſoeuer this ſeeme to equalize common fellons to them, for as much as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21132:35"/> according to the preſent ſtate, their executions differ not in ſenſe but in ſhame, yet if we conſider all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, we ſhall finde, firſt that this death by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine cuts off the ordinary meanes of repentance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it exceedeth the patience of mans nature, and driues him to vnexpected diſpaire, and obſtinacie: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it ſhall appeare, that this auncient cruelty would now too much harden our hearts, more then ſufficiently frozen ouer with the inſenſible yſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION VI.</head>
                  <p>AN other ſuppoſed enemy of iuſtice, is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Vſurie, which indeed if it be exerciſed to the poore, or to rich without reſpect of damage in ſuing, may be intollerable; but in caſe of intereſt when time of payment is neglected, in the ſtate of Orphants, in mutual hazard, or in hazard publike, ſimply to diſſalow it, is to cut of all traffique and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, for this ſinne is rather in the conſcience then in the act, therefore no penalty is impoſed vpon it by Gods law; true it is, our lawes tollerate ten in the hundreth, but the intent, not the rigor thereof is to be weighed, for the clearing of iuſtice: the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall lawes which appointed ſixe, eight or twelue in the hundreth, do ſhew there is great difference in the moderation of theſe matters, which Prudence onely directs as the loadſtone doth the variation of the Pole.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21132:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> New Names of Conſtancie Abſtinence, and Shamefaſtneſſe.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing runne ouer the perfect vertues, it followeth next, we ſhould entreate of thoſe which are counted dimidiate and imperfect, the firſt is conſtancie, an appendent to fortitude, which is a perſeuerance in doing good with reſiſtance of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo that except wee will bee Stoickes, who baniſh affections ſpecially obſtinate, Fortitude is a vertue which ſhould be; Conſtancie which is for whilſt we liue in this clay, this generation of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is <hi>Laſciuis hederis ambitioſior,</hi> and ſtickes like a horſe-leach, drawing bloud till it burſt, but euen this imperfect vertue, is perfectly ouerſhadowed, firſt with obſtinacie, which ſeruilefieth a man to his will ſo that hee becomes like <hi>Moecenas,</hi> a thouſand times married to the ſame wife, alwayes iarring, yet alwayes faint to bee reconciled; the ground of this phrenſie is, that men will, before they deliberate; firſt executing the Priſoner, then enquiring of his demerite as men ſay they doe at Halifax, or as ſome haue done in religion firſt broching a new doctrine, then ſetting Clarkes a worke to maintaine it by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite argument: this obſtinacy feedes hereſie, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21132:36"/> the vapor of the adioyning Sea doth the flame in Mount Aetna, which breakes out euery third<note place="margin">Thucidides, lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> yeare, the onely medicine of this fanſie, is <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum a fuſtibus,</hi> flat violence vpon iniurie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſhall finde beſt experience, that dealeth with Mariners, or vntutored Barbarians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>ANother ſoyling of conſtancy, is an immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate kind of ſelfe-loue, ſuch as <hi>Pamphilus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tends in Arcadia, who though he loued many by a ſucceſsiue mutabilitie, yet proued that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, by this reaſon: The thing which I loued was my fancie affecting her, when that fleeted to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtill I purſued the ſame fancie, and therefore cannot be accus'd of inconſtancie, which is as much as if hee had made himſelfe the Center, and had drawne all lines of the Circle, from the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of his actions to that one vndiuided point. By this rule ſome Politicians, all pennie-fathers haue beene ſo guided, that as Lyons and other beaſts are led by the ſent in the night to their pray, ſo theſe by their owne ſelfe-loue are drawne to each deſire and action, ſo that where they find not <hi>bonum coniunctum</hi> as they terme it, they relinquiſh it as vnſociable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21132:36"/>
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond imperfect vertue is abſtinence, or continence, which is a temperance with the combat of affections, this combat in caſe of luſt <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines</hi> call burning, according to the ſaying, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Marrie then to burne. Now burning is not onely an aſſent after abſtraction and ineſcation, commonly called the firſt motion and delight, but rather a continuall ſoliciting of the minde, together with an auocation, from the ordinarie functions of a mans vocation. Here is then the vulgar error, to ſuppoſe each tickling of the minde to bee burning, and ſo to imply a neceſſitie of Matrimonie, whereas indeede if a man abſtaine both from lawleſſe actes, and bee withall ſo laborious in his calling, that hee can (though with ſome difficultie) repell theſe fierie aſſaults, he may be truely termed continent.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si valeant homines, ars tua Phoebe iacet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If men be aye in temper iuſt, <hi>Phoebus</hi> thy Arte ſhall lie in duſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>If there bee no contention or reſiſtance, how ſhall a man promiſe to himſelfe, that after <hi>Hymens</hi> rites, he ſhall not yeeld to his owne adulterous ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THe third inchoate vertue is Shamefaſtneſſe, in ancient times much praiſed in yong men, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21132:37"/> then in olde men, now in both, ſaue that ſome haue found a new Name for their Paleneſſe, at the recitall of their vnrepented villanies, which they haue clothed with the maiden-like robes of bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Whereas indeede bluſhing is but a feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke for an error, vpon miſpriſion or miſtaking, not a dead wanneſſe for a fault, which a man neuer in tends to leaue till it forſake him, this is nothing but the ſtripes or ſtreaked colours of conſcience, <hi>Quae cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co verbere torquet,</hi> Like the rods which are made in the clouds, but bluſhing &amp; faſting are baniſht toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one being accuſed of ignorance, the other of rigorouſnes: The firſt was confined to Terra Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida, or ſome ſuch Countrey, where ignorance of vice ſeemes to doe more good, then the knowledge of vertue, the latter was ſhipt ouer into the Ile of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> The Frenzies of Friendſhip.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendſhip not a vertue, but the reflexion of vertues in two, as being a mutual loue not lurking, doeth change her Name as often as the Sea. which heere is called <hi>Aegeum,</hi> there <hi>Ionium,</hi> elſewhere <hi>Adriaticke, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantic, Perſic,</hi> and the like. The firſt Name, is Loue,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21132:37"/> which like the fiſh Polypus, aſſumes the colour of a Rocke, to which it ſtickes; ſo doth this, of friendſhip, here is onely the difference, the fiſh deludeth other fiſhes onely, this it ſelfe principally; but tell mee, what is loue? A Mule is a beaſt begott of a horſe and a ſhee Aſſe: ſo loue is an humour begot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene wit and idleneſſe, and to omit other imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it hath borrowed the names of two famous Artes, inſomuch that the Artes themſelues are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt, if ſome ſmall ſhards of them had not been digged out of the monuments of antiquity, the firſt is Muſicke, the Theorie whereof is almoſt abrogated by Arithmeticall and Geometricall proportions, ſo celebrated in <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and his followers, and now layde in <hi>Democritus</hi> pit, where hee buried truth: the practiſe alſo of Muſicke is deformed by amorous <hi>Lyricks,</hi> whoſe Sonets are nothing but bellows of contemplatiue luſt, of whome may be ſaid what <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenall</hi> ſayth of women:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Haec faciunt, quibus accendi iam frigidus aeuo</l>
                     <l>Laomedontiades, &amp; Neſtoris hernia poſſet.<note place="margin">Satyr. 6. Set downe by Sir Thomas Eliot in his gouernment. li. 1. cap. 20. 21.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>To pretermit other innouations, the Art of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing with the miſteries thereof, which was an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant of Muſicke, is now made the mother of toyes, and whereas in ancient times it ſerued <hi>Mars, Minerua, Ceres,</hi> and <hi>Pan,</hi> Warre, Learning, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry and Shepheards, now forſooth Dame <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> hath made an impropriation of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:21132:38"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Art, which this <hi>Circe</hi> with her wand hath inchanted, is Poetrie, by her Syren ſonges drawne downe from the toppe of Parnaſſus, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to the vale of Taenarus. The Duke of Vrbins Painter, being commaunded to draw the ſhape of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> drew the face ſomewhat red. other pointes of his workemanſhippe were commended. but when a doubt was moued of this, hee anſwered that indeed they were ſomewhat pale with prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but were they now aliue, a vermilion bluſh would dye their faces, to ſee the lazie fattneſſe of their imagined ſucceſſors: ſo I thinke, if a man would paint <hi>Homer, Heſiod, Aratus, Nicander, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horace. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dta Drrcaeum leuat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Heroicke Poets: or the Tragedians, <hi>AEſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Sophocles, Lycophron,</hi> or that famous Theban Swan, <hi>Pindirus</hi> the Prince of the Lyrickes, or the Latine Poets, <hi>Virgil, Claudian, Lucan, Statius,</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſhould all be painted bluſhing, to ſee <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides, Theocritus, Catullus, Ouid, Martial,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſeruing <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Mineruas</hi> rayment: if wee conſider thoſe heauenly Poets, <hi>Moſes, Iob, Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dauid, Eſay, Habacuk,</hi> or thoſe of a lower ranke, but yet diuine, <hi>Nonnus, Apollinarius, Serra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> wee ſhall ſee that the moſt excellent ſubiectes were ſelected for Poetrie, that the wiſeſt Princes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Prophets, moſt learned Prieſtes, thought them ſelues honoured by this Arte: but now pardon me you <hi>Manes Homerici, &amp; Virgiliani,</hi> ſhee is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21132:38"/> 
                     <hi>Trulla,</hi> I had almoſt ſaid the Trull of lewde loues, fancies and paſſions: redeeme her from this ſhame, if any ſinew of <hi>Spencer</hi> be left in you, and let it be a capitall fault <hi>in Virginis choro,</hi> I meane <hi>Pallas, Veneris torum vel nominaſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>GRieuous it is, that the wolfe ſhould deuoure the Lambe, but when the Lambe eates the Lambe, what Southſayer would not bee amaſed? Friendſhip to be iniured by vice, is euill, but no wonder; but it is a wondrous euill that a vertue, namely Concord, ſhould doe her wrong, yet ſo it is, ſome men thinke they ſhould haue concord with all men, friendſhip with none: by concord they vnderſtand peaceable conuerſation, vpon reſpects of mutuall gaine, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, honour; by friendſhipp, they fancy a thing in abſtract or rather in the cloudes, a perfect ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of manners, ſtudies, age, degree, with coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, a thing ſcarſely to be expected in heauen, where although loue haue <hi>Temperamentum ad pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> (as they ſay in Phyſicke) yet as a ſtarre exceedeth a ſtarre in one of the ſixe magnitudes, ſo ſoule ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth ſoule in glorie: all the cupps are full of Nectar, yet one ſurpaſſeth another in capable quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity: wherefore vpon this pretence, that friendſhipp cannot bee more then Celeſtiall, to abandon the golden linckes of friendſhipp, and to vſe onely the baſe coine of common concord, is a greater ſigne
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21132:39"/> of ſuſpition then of vertue, wee doe like the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp of Saintes, not onely by the light of faith, but partly led thereto by reaſon: <hi>Antigona</hi> could ſay, that ſhee ought to pleaſe thoſe, with whome ſhee<note place="margin">Sophocles in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigona.</note> hoped to remaine for euer, meaning thereby the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of Heauen: So if <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Plato,</hi> and <hi>Sybilla</hi> in <hi>Virgil,</hi> doe tell vs that heauen, or Elyſium is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for good men, wee ought to bee acquainted in this ſea, that when wee arriue at the hoped Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, wee may enioy the ioy of indiſſoluble friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe: and although concord make a good Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, yet hee that wants friendſhipp, is but a bad man, for a good Citizen and a good man are not all one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>COmbinations of thieues, of them that follow the Lupercals, of Rebels, of Heretickes, haue<note place="margin">Obſcene ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Pan.</note> alſo challenged the name of friendſhipp, as if ſhee were a Camelion, admitting all colours but red and white; the former being a ſymbole of modeſtie, the latter of integrity: Certaine it is, that vnion not of minds, but of cauſes, makes friendſhippe, elſe this vertue might be found in <hi>Plutoes</hi> guard, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Nimphes that watch about Acharon, Styx, Lethe, Cocytus, Peryphlegeton, the fiue loathſome Lakes of hatefull hell: yet ſo it is, theſe ſeeming ſocieties, or rather conſpiracies, vſing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in diſorder, I meane in the feaſtes of <hi>Bona Dea,</hi>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21132:39"/> that is of good fellowſhip, haue made a Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all neighbourhood, as if the better ſort did liue like <hi>Apri ſingulares &amp; Solivagi,</hi> ſolitary wandring Boares, whereas theſe good Wolues pray together, though it may be, they neuer praied but in a ſtorm, in which. if <hi>Bias</hi> had beene with them, hee would haue deſired their ſilence, leſt that God hearing their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo contrary to their deedes, ſhould as contrary to their wils drowne them in the ſeas, as they with their wils had drowned themſelues in the dead ſea of pleaſure. But here is the error, they cannot be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">See the Legend of Phaedria in the 2. booke of the Fayerie Queene.</note> except they laugh a Sardonian laughter, <hi>qui plus Alloes quam Mellis habet,</hi> which turneth at laſt to wormewood, or rather to the worme that neuer dyes, and the burning wood, whoſe conſumption ſhall neuer receiue conſummation: but the truth is, this violent amity cannot be perpetuall; when Apes ſees Nuts, and Serpents Bettany, they leaue their dauncing and hiſſing concord, and fight a Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mion fight to winne a bloody victory, where the Conquerour weepes, and hee that is conquered is vndone.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>THe pluralitie of friends, is not the leaſt Viper eating out the heart of friendſhip, and yet as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamie</hi> will needes be Mariage, howſoeuer in latter times it is accounted adulterie: ſo he that hath many friends, thinkes hee hath much friendſhip. Well,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21132:40"/> 
                     <hi>Adrian</hi> ſaid truely, by the multitude of Phyſicians<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the Emperour is dead, ſo I ſuppoſe, friendſhip being<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tus in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> *Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s is Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on in the 2. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne.</note> diſtracted like the riuer * Gingdes, by Cyrus into three hundreth ſixtie fiue Brookes, to looſe both her Name and nature. An old man in the Fable at his death, demanded his Sonne what friends he had, the yong man anſwered very many: Well ſaid hee, I haue liued ſo long, and yet haue found but halfe a friend, you therefore for your inſtruction doe thus: Kill a Calfe and put it in a ſacke, goe to your friends and tell them tis a child, whom you haue murthered, requeſting them to burie and conceale it, the yong man obeying, found that his friends ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke him off, as a Spaniell comming to land, ſhakes the water off his haire, then at his Fathers aduiſe hee went to his halfe friend, who preſently aſſented to it, meane while one of this yong-mans friends accuſed him, and had ſent him to Charon before his Father, had not the matter beene diſcouered, we need not Print the meaning of this tale. Tis plaine, that as he that had his haire halfe Gray halfe Blacke, being Married to a yong and an old wife, the yong pulling off the Gray, the old the Blacke, he became Balde before he was craftie, ſo hee that diuides his friendſhip, as the harlot would haue had the child before <hi>Salomon,</hi> may Marrie with friendſhip by the Popes old Law, for he is aboue ſeuen degrees from it. We haue read one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Dauid</hi> that had two friend, <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>Huſha,</hi> but the latter was not his friend, till many yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the former: Some thinke <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> had two friends, <hi>Maecenas</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21132:40"/> the former was ſo garrulous, the latter ſo impatient, that he had much adoe to ſhunne the one, and beare with the other. And whereas ſome make <hi>Poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o,</hi> to be the third, <hi>Dion</hi> refutes that errour, ſhewing that <hi>Poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> was ſo cruell, that when <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stus</hi> came to ſuppe with him, he commanded one of his ſeruants for breaking a Chriſtal glaſſe, to be caſt to his Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prees, that they might deuoure him aliue, but <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus</hi> calling for all the Chriſtals in the houſe, brake them, and ſaued the ſeruant, and afterward he demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed <hi>Pollioes</hi> houſe, though hee gaue it him on his death bed. By this declaring that Princes may haue many wel-willers, but few friends, for the friends of great men dwell either at the Citie Trapezus, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a Table, or at Placentia, ſo named <hi>a placendo,</hi> but few either at Verona, or Conſtantia, few are either ſo true or conſtant, that they will not hold their friends as men doe Wolues by the eares, not able to retaine, and fearing to let goe. Moſt cleare it is, that the noble paires of friends, <hi>Orestes</hi> and <hi>Pylades, Niſus</hi> and <hi>Eurialus, Damon</hi> and <hi>Pytheas, Scipio</hi> and <hi>Lelius, Cicero</hi> and <hi>Atticus, Ieſippus</hi> and <hi>Fuluius,</hi> and in the Arcadia, <hi>Muſidorus</hi> and <hi>Pyrocles,</hi> are no leſſe extold by <hi>Aristoes</hi> two Swannes, <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> and <hi>Poeſie,</hi> then <hi>Dichotomies</hi> are by <hi>Ramiſts,</hi> or the quadrature of the Circle, and the Philoſophers ſtone by them that neuer knew them. To ſeale vp all, we will haue <hi>Catoes</hi> poſie in his Ring: <hi>Esto inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus nullius, vnius amicus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21132:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Vaine Titles of heroycall Vertue.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ertue according to the Stoickes, was diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into <hi>Cathecon</hi> and <hi>Catorthoma,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Cicero. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ic. 1.</note> into Vertue meane and poſſible, or Vertue tranſcendent and heroycall, ſuch as the Scriptures aſcribe to <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the Poets their Apes to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and our writers to Prince <hi>Arthur.</hi> This vertue hath beene three wayes aſſaulted, Firſt, by calumniation, for actions done by diuine inſtinct, haue euer found ſome <hi>Zoylus, Momus, Mastix,</hi> or<note place="margin">See Spencer. lib. 6.</note> tongue of blattant beaſt, ſo called of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to hurt. Hence commeth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, dammage, from which it may be, our word Blab doeth fetch his Pedigree. The deedes of <hi>Sampſon</hi> are ſcoft at by many, not knowing with what ſpirit he did them, as for them that carpe at the acts of <hi>Hercules,</hi> wee pittie their braines, becauſe they vnderſtand not the Poets di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine intent, which was to deſcribe a man indued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede with eminent Vertues, yet not exempt from humaine paſſions, and therefore they faine him drunke, and mad, and that which is worſe then both, ſo drunke and mad with the loue of <hi>Omphale,</hi> that he ſerued her in a womans habit. Not vnlike things doe <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Statius</hi> aſcribe to <hi>Achilles,</hi> neither is <hi>Homers Vliſſes</hi> free from all tincture of folly: Yea
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21132:41"/> 
                     <hi>Virgil</hi> the Prince of Helicon, decyphering in his <hi>Aeneas,</hi> the valour of <hi>Achilles</hi> in the Iliads, and the wiſedome of <hi>Vliſſes</hi> in the Odyſſes, is not blamed for writing that verſe,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Speluncam Dido dux &amp; Troianus eandem<note place="margin">AEneiad. 4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Deueniunt.—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Who knowes not what followed, and how ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee was rebuked from <hi>Iupiter</hi> by <hi>Mercurie.</hi> But ſome Aſſe that neuer taſted of the Modals will ſay, why doe you bring your patterns from braine ſicke Poets? to whome wee ſhape this anſwere, not onely theſe which lie not, becauſe they ſay they lie; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe which cannot erre, haue ſet downe men of heroycall vertues, yet darkened like the Moone with ſome blot; therefore as well the ſinnes as the vertues of <hi>Moſes, Sampſon, Dauid</hi> are regiſtred with the point of a Diamond in the glaſſe of true hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, ſeeing none can truely challenge that to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which the Haſell tree ſaid in <hi>Ouid,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nux ego iuncta viae, quae ſum ſine crimine vitae,</l>
                     <l>A populo ſaxis pretereunte petor.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſilly Nut-tree bordering on the way,</l>
                     <l>Which in my life did neuer erre or ſtray,</l>
                     <l>With ſtaues and ſtones in maner rude</l>
                     <l>Am pelted by the multitude.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Or thus,</head>
                     <l>I faultleſſe Nut-tree ioyned to the way,</l>
                     <l>With ſtones and ſtaues am pelted euery day.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21132:42"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THe next impeachment of Heroycall vertue is Apiſh imitation, to which may be applyed that of <hi>Horace,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pindarum quiſque ſtudet aemulari,</l>
                     <l>Iuli ceratis ope Dedalea</l>
                     <l>Nititur pennis, vitreo daturus</l>
                     <l>—Nomina Ponto.<note place="margin">Horace Ode. 2</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iulus,</hi> who ſtriues <hi>Pindar</hi> to emulate,</l>
                     <l>With waxen wings which <hi>Dedal's</hi> arte did make;</l>
                     <l>He flies in vaine, to giue by hapleſſe fate,</l>
                     <l>Names to the Icarian, glaſſie, blewiſh lake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>We reade of <hi>Salmoneus</hi> imitating <hi>Iupiters</hi> thunder, and ſo puniſhed by it.</p>
                  <q>Vidi &amp; crudeles dantem Salmonea poenas.</q>
                  <note place="margin">Aeneid. 6.</note>
                  <p>By which is inſinuated that actions diuine or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, are not with emulation to be followed, but to bee adored with admiration; for this in other things is moſt ridiculous, in religion moſt perilous, of which hereafter. <hi>Antonius</hi> that would in all points be <hi>Alexander, Alexander</hi> himſelfe that would bee ſon of <hi>Iupiter Hammon, Commodus</hi> for imitating <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> and <hi>Nero Phoebus,</hi> both in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inging and driuing Chariots, are read of with as much laughter being dead, as being aliue, they were feared with hatred: <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>crinus</hi> in Herodian is much condemned for his vaine perſiſting in the ſteppes of good <hi>Pertinax,</hi> wearing like the Cuman Aſſe the Lyons skinne, till
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21132:42"/> the ſtranger that had ſeene a Lyon, knew him by his eares and braying. <hi>Caligula</hi> would needs imitate <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar</hi> in conquering <hi>Britaine,</hi> and conducting his Armie to the ſea ſide, commaunded his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to gather ſhelles, which hee called the ſpoiles of the Ocean, and binding a few Germanes that neuer fought againſt him, led them in triumph to Rome; with many other things, which <hi>Dion, Suetonius,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> alſo, if that part of him were extant, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, not becauſe they ſhould moue the ſpleene, but that wee may ſee how Princes haue beene flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in things ſo abſurde, in ſo much that <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> had like to haue beene put to death, becauſe he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in ſome ſort to bee weary of <hi>Neroes</hi> ſinging; and <hi>Corbuto</hi> was killed before hand, becauſe it was thought he would diſlike it when he came: and this certainely hath beene the meanes to encreaſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency of many Tyrants, that once takinga con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, that they were like ſome famous Prince; their humour being found and followed by ſome worſe then Crowes, feeding vpon the faults of the liuing, not vpon the carkaſes of the dead, haue withall cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty endeauoured to make good their firſt fancy. <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus</hi> the Emperour thought himſelfe ſo like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> that when a Lawyer in a Plea with one of that name, did crie out, O wicked <hi>Alexander!</hi> O the manners of <hi>Alexander!</hi> what ſhall bee done to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander?</hi> at length in great choler anſwered, if you doe not quickly ceaſe reyling of <hi>Alexander,</hi> you ſhall feele great <hi>Alexanders</hi> power. If I ſhould tell at large the like things of <hi>Commodus,</hi> I ſhould write out the<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21132:43"/> propounded by <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> how the Nobility was reputed, he told the people which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted from the Nobility, that the ſtomacke was once forſaken by the members of the body, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playning, that it was idle, and they endured all the labour for it; In concluſion, the ſtomacke fainting, they likewiſe quailed, and too late agniſed their owne errour. This parable ſo moued the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that they neuer after vpon any mutiny labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wholly to aboliſh, but to qualifie and moderate the Nobility: and howſoeuer in the ciuill warres of <hi>Scylla,</hi> and <hi>Marius, Cinna</hi> and <hi>Sertorius, Pompey, Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Caeſar, Anthonie, Lepidus</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the Nobilitie was much impaired, yet <hi>Auguſtus</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his publicke prouidence, repayred and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured the Senate, augmenting their Reuenewes, purging their infamies, and at leaſt in appearance, confirming their authorities: And this as it was not neglected by <hi>Tyberius,</hi> ſo was it mainely reſpected by <hi>Veſpaſian, Nerua, Traian, Aurelius, Pertinax,</hi> and other Emperours, no leſſe worthy of a <hi>Maeonian</hi> Trumpet then <hi>Achilles.</hi> The Venetians, Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and they of Genoa haue moſt curiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame; but Venice is moſt famous for it, as appeares by that excellent Epigram:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not <hi>Marke</hi> but <hi>Mercury</hi> doth keepe her warme,</l>
                     <l>And Sea-God <hi>Neptune</hi> hugges her in his arme:</l>
                     <l>Fertill, though vnfertill of all good things,</l>
                     <l>Her Prince a Monarch, and her children Kings.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>For the Nobility is intereſſed in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, neyther doe I thinke, that any State, eyther
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21132:43"/> auncient or moderne, can be preferred to it for pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke and diſcreete Gouernement: It were labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to recite, and tedious to heare, how, as when Bees are decayed, they are reuiued by the death of an Oxe; ſo Nobilitie hath beene often repaired in Fraunce, England, and elſe-where. When the two Roſes in England, the redde and the white, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beene made redde with the blood of thirteene ſet battels, yet care was had by that ſecond <hi>Salomon,</hi> I meane that renowned <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, that out of the aſhes of the olde Nobility, a new Phoenix might be raiſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THE ſecond error concerning Nobility is, that birth alone is Magnanimity or Heroycall vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: this hath ſufficiently beene refeld by <hi>Agrippa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De vanitate Scientiar. Saty. 15. Saty. 2.</note> by <hi>Iuuenall,</hi> by <hi>Perſius,</hi> but eſpecially by <hi>Maximili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> foole, for when he deſired to bring his Petegree to <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, he told him, that whereas now he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced him like a God, if he came once to the Arke, he ſhould be his fellow; for he was ſure, that he alſo deſcended from thence. Furthermore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this ſucceſſiue Nobility, theſe things are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: Firſt, that children ſo borne, ſeldome enlarge their fathers gouernement, but reſting contented with their atchieuements, ſettle vppon their lees: Secondly, theſe men comming with eaſe to authority, being trained vp in a flattered educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21132:44"/> doe eaſily degenerate to all lawleſſe licence; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Commodus</hi> are euident: Nay, <hi>Herodian</hi> ſheweth, that this conſideration greatly<note place="margin">Herodian l. 1.</note> moleſted <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> vpon his death-bed; and therefore both the ſame <hi>Marcus,</hi> and <hi>Pertinax;</hi> yea and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> himſelfe twice indeede: likewiſe <hi>Tybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Seuerus</hi> alwaies in ſhew, a tempted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Common-wealth to the Gouernement, by election, not by ſucceſſion. But although it be true, that ſometimes ignorant or euill Princes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, yet the condition of Kingdomes and Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not alike; for although the King be inſufficient, yet his peaceable ſucceſſion preuents inteſtine mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies, ſpecially if the Councellers be wiſe; and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine inuaſions doe not approach: but when the children of Nobles are weake or wicked; it will be hard to find a domeſticall remedie: Thirdly, we find a Common-wealth not to be durable, where linkes of order are not equall in proportion of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, for in nature we ſee, that the Elements are ioyned by <hi>Symbolization,</hi> the ayre to the fire by warmeneſſe, the water to the ayre by moyſture, the<note place="margin">Parcite Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopho manes Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceroniani &amp; Syd mani.</note> earth to the water by coldneſſe; but where Nobles are without regard of vertue, there is no deſcending by ſtayres, but eyther a Peſant or a Gentleman, a Dolphin or a Dog-fiſh, an accident or a ſubſtance: Laſtly, meere Nobility is commonly the ruine of the family; for hee that is noble without vertue, proues ignoble by extraordinary vices of his owne, or deuiſes of others: wherefore it is expedient that the Temples of vertue and honour be built together
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21132:44"/> as it was in Rome, and that euery man take great birth, to be an obligation of vertue made vnto him: It was ominous in <hi>Xerxes</hi> Armie, when a Mare<note place="margin">Iuſtine.</note> brought foorth a Hare, for it was a ſigne that his great Army ſhould be ſurpriſed with prodigious cowardiſe: no leſſe monſtrous is it to ſee <hi>Thyrſites</hi> come of <hi>Achilles,</hi> to ſee <hi>Samias Ninias</hi> the ſonne of great <hi>Ninus,</hi> drunken <hi>Cambiſes</hi> of ſober <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Marcus</hi> to whom <hi>Cicero</hi> dedicated his Offices, to liue as much baſelyer then his father, as his father did more honourable then his Aunceſtors: Who mournes not to heare the two ſonnes of <hi>Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> more inferiour to the meaneſt, then hee was ſuperiour to the beſt: it is a griefe to a Prince, when neceſſity inforceth him to fill his Councell-Table and places of truſt, with men of meane diſcent, whileſt the Nobility clayme their fathers titles and titles of honour, and yet are neyther ſent to warre, nor rule in Iudgement; as being eyther vnable or vnwilling: but in our land there be no Wolues, and I hope neyther Owles nor Aſſes: we deteſt the Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> that laide this imputation vpon vs, whether vpon error or wilfully we know not, but certainely we haue had, and haue many buds of true Nobility, which haue brought forth the fruites of Magnanimity and heroycall vertue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21132:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> New Names of Arts.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moral Vertues being handled, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to treate of the intellectuall, which commonly are reckoned fiue, Wiſedome, Vnderſtanding, Science, Prudence, Arte. But I know not by what infelicitie, Art and Science, haue vnder their names comprehended the reſt, as the Romane Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions in the dayes of the Emperours, were growen into diſordered numbers, ſo that one contained the quantitie of many, before ordained in the time of good Militarie diſcipline. Arts are of ſundry kinds, ſome inſtrumentall, Grammer, Rhetoricke, Logick, but theſe three are ſpeciall, the generall bee <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> and <hi>Poeſie,</hi> the others bee principall, and they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Contemplatiue or Practicke. The former is diuided into Metaphyſickes, Phyſickes, and Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, vnder the laſt whereof, are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Arithmeticke, Muſicke, Geometrie, Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: The latter be parted into <hi>actiue</hi> and <hi>factiue, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> be <hi>Ethicke, Oeconomicke, Politicke</hi> vnder which is the Ciuill Law and Art of war. The <hi>Factiue,</hi> are all mechanicke Arts, as Medicine, Husbandry, Cooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Building, Armorie, Cloathing, Shipping: Now to tell the falſe names of theſe, would require a tenth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21132:45"/> Muſe or an other <hi>Scaliger.</hi> In whom <hi>Salust</hi> ſaid, was<note place="margin">Dubartus.</note> the Babylon of learning: Firſt Grammer hath got a new name of <hi>Critickes,</hi> who haue found out the bleſſed Arte of changing words, when they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them not, to whom may agree the cenſure gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> by <hi>Lipſius, Magnus</hi> Eraſmus <hi>fuit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See Sauils Notes vpon a place of Polibius, in the end of his Notes of Tacitus Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie.</note> 
                     <hi>maior fuiſſet, ſi minor eſſe voluiſſet,</hi> And I thinke the Authour of this cenſure, if hee diſſembled not in his Notes vpon <hi>Tacitus,</hi> as he did in his Booke <hi>De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia,</hi> was not a little ſorie of his time torne in theſe toyes. For that which the famous Geographer of<note place="margin">Camden in his Britanie.</note> England ſaid of Norfolke-men, that they ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout tittles in Law when Titles faile: May as truely agree to theſe Crickets, I ſhould ſay <hi>Critickes,</hi> who fill their Bookes with <hi>Variae lectiones,</hi> and tell you a long ſtorie where they borrowed this Manuſcript, where they ſaw that Monument, how this coniect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure may be good, thoſe commaes may be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to colons, and colons into periods, but I am wearie with ſpeaking of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>RHetoricke now baniſht out of Turkie, as it was out of Sparta, hath alwayes claimed the name of Patronage, whereupon ſome imagine our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to haue bene ſucceſſors of the ancient Orators. True it is, that many Pleaes are found in <hi>Tacitus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Senators that gained by pleading, but there alſo they are refuted. Neither can I but agree to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21132:46"/> that ſaying of <hi>Littleton,</hi> that good pleading is a thing moſt honourable, rayling and delayes haue beene the ſtaines of this profeſſion, ſome haue beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for falſification, ſome for <hi>Ambo-dexters:</hi> But we may not blame the vſe of the calling, for the abuſe of the men. The Diuel was an Angel, <hi>Balaam</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and <hi>Iudas</hi> an Apoſtle. Though ſome Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers haue beene thought to haue beene lyers, yet <hi>Fitz-harbert, Ployden, Bracton</hi> and <hi>Stamford,</hi> cannot<note place="margin">Juris prudentes vocantur iure prudentes.</note> without great malice and parcialitie, receiue theſe imputations, and certainely in the Apologie of Rhetorician Lawyers, it may bee ſaid: Firſt, that if they ſhould not vſe much volubilitie of tongue, the multitude would not admire, and ſo not reuerence them. Secondly, where the ſound of Warre is not, there of neceſſitie muſt bee either mutinies, or Law. Thirdly, if Law were not coſtly and tedious, and like the vpper Mil-ſtone, as Vſurie is compared to the neather, the vulgar ſort which are as malicious as Witches, would vſe Lawes frequently, as foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball play, or dauncing about a May-pole, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this may bee as good an inſtruction to them, as that which a merrie man ſaid, hearing there were many things to bee decreed in Parliament againſt Ale-houſes: I warrant you quoth hee, it was at the motion of ſome Lawyer, for a dozzen of Ale would end more Suites at one ſitting, then would bee ſpun ouer in three Tearmes. Fourthly, the multiplicitie of Caſes, doth of neceſſitie imply many querkes, and therefore the <hi>Rabbins</hi> haue found many quiddities in <hi>Moſes</hi> law vpon the like occaſion: Nay, ſuppoſe the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21132:46"/> Alcheron it ſelfe, were it not ruled by barbarous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie, would admit endleſſe ſcruples. Laſtly, if the Law were not full of ambiguities, witte, experience, eloquence, ſhould haue no place: onely it were to be wiſhed, that the Orphane, the Widdow, and the needy, ſhould not by delayes <hi>&amp; dimurrurs</hi> be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. I ſhould ſpeake of Logicke and Poetrie, but vpon other occaſions I haue before treated of them, onely this I will adde, I doe heartily wiſh that ſome great <hi>Mecaenas</hi> would maintaine perpetuall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of thoſe two Arts, as alſo of Rhetoricke, and Mathematickes in the Academies, for then wee ſhould not be ſcorned in foraine Vniuerſities.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>HIſtory the witneſſe of time, and the memory of truth, hath alſo receiued much obſcurity, firſt, by the neglect of Chronologie, which among the Grecians is obſerued onely by <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> for <hi>Thucidides</hi> writes but of a ſmall time, ſo doth <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> that ſupplyed him. <hi>Polybius</hi> is almoſt all loſt: againe, many fables haue beene inſerted, as appeares not onely in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> but euen in <hi>Plutarch</hi> and in <hi>Liuie;</hi> yea our Eccleſiaſticall ſtory hath beene found full of lying Legends, beſides this the, deſire of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction greatly Eclipſed the light of ſtory, of which our moderne Chronicles are ſufficient teſtimonies, alſo the ſtudy of inſerting too many orations, things indeed reproued by <hi>Diodorus, Iuſtine, Herodian,</hi> haue
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21132:47"/> hindered Authors from inquiring into more matter, and ſo haue ſtarued the ſtudious Reader, the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Geographie hath beene no leſſe impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the glory of Hiſtory: there bee alſo acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall miſeries much to be deplored, as firſt the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of vnlearned Tyrants, which haue ſacrificed to <hi>Vulean</hi> ſo many labours of <hi>Minerua,</hi> as alſo that Readers and profeſſors of this Arte, haue not beene dreampt of in our Vniuerſities, much leſſe maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and honoured: for he that will bee a good Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, muſt let all other ploughes ſtand ſtill whileſt he liues.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THe ſcience Metaphyſicall is like a man, that hath a Spaniſh geſture, an Italian eye, a Dutch ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, an Indian breath, a Negroes Venerie, and a French ſuite, for it hath borrowed ſome plumes from Logicke, ſome from Diuinity, ſome from Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, the lands are not out of finall recouerie, therfore may be ſued for: in a word, this ſcience is <hi>non ens,</hi> a vacuity without a body, a name without nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>NAturall Philoſophy, were indeede a thing, and not a name onely, if men ſpent not their time, al in the Generals of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> neuer deſcending to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21132:47"/> particulars in <hi>Geſner,</hi> and to the practiſe in <hi>Galen,</hi> for certaine it is that Phyſickes without Phyſicke are clouds without water, and Phyſicke it ſelfe without knowledge of birdes, beaſtes, fiſhes, and creeping things is lame and barren: here alſo the want of Readers in perpetuity, were to bee renued, if eyther liberall men were learned, or vnlearned men would belieue the skilfull; but alas, there is a froſt of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the yce of Auarice hath ſo couered ouer the water of Liberality, that the fiſhes in the riuer Helicon, are in as bad a taking, as thoſe in the great froſt, when the verſe of <hi>Virgil</hi> was verified.</p>
                  <q>—<hi>Caeduntque ſecuribus humida vina.</hi>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VI.</head>
                  <p>THe Mathematicall Arts, were it not for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and want of maintenance, would not be naked names, but things of eaſe and vſe: of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke I ſpake before, Arithmeticke is no more inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into, then that it may be a band to couetouſnes: Geometrie with the Optickes, and Aſtronomy are too laborious and coſtly for our idle and needy age, ſo that mad men and Mathematitians, Alminacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers and lyers are almoſt confounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VII.</head>
                  <p>EThickes and Politickes haue beene handled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Arte Oeconomicke is partly ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21132:48"/> vp in Diuinity, partly couered vnder the winges of Auarice, but with the pretence of frugality: the true practiſe thereof in Education of children is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle knowne, leſſe regarded, for the rich will not, the poore cannot bring vpp their Children, as they ſhould, ſo that our preſent lazineſſe and ignorance, are truer then Prognoſtications of our barbariſme, Atheiſme, and ruine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VIII.</head>
                  <p>ARtes Mechanicke or Factiue, are ſlubbered o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with many neglects or curioſities, tillage by the couetouſneſſe of a few is made a trade of beggerie, Cookery by the daintineſſe of ſome, is become a Stewes of Luxurie; the Art of Phyſicke otherwiſe moſt honourable, profitable, pleaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the vnlearned, idle, haſty, cruell, couetous diſpoſitions of many, is abaſed among the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as if it were a trade of Butchers or murtherers: Architecture with Geometrie is decayed, Armorie by too much peace is growne ruſtie: of Veſtiture, we ſpake before: Shipping onely and Marchandiſe now remaine in better caſe then other trades, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede one Mechanicke Arte hath deuoured all the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall,<note place="margin">Aenei. lib. 3.</note> as the Harpies did <hi>AEneas</hi> ſupper.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:21132:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> New Names of falſe Religions.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen all Creatures had beene fram'de—</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sanctius his Animal, mentiſque capacius altae</l>
                     <l>Deerat adhuc, &amp; quod dominari in caetera poſſit.<note place="margin">Metamor. lib. 1</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>So all Arts being handled, ſacred Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty remayneth, which as it is moſt pure and Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, ſo being corrupted becomes moſt diueliſh: the maine corruption thereof is called falſe Religion: and of this kind, the firſt was Paganiſme, Hel eniſme,<note place="margin">Helleni ſme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Greekes, that worſhip many Gods. Aeneid. 8.</note> or Polutheiſme, for which Egypt was infamous, as the Poet ſaith;</p>
                  <q>Omnigenumque Deum monstra &amp; latrator Anubis.</q>
                  <p>The greateſt couſenage in this kind, was of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as that of Dodona, where <hi>Iupiter</hi> anſwered, ſtriking the Caldrons with a ſiluer wand: that of <hi>Iupiter Hammon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> in the confines of Aegypt, that of the Trees of the Sunne and Moone, ſpeaking partly<note place="margin">Curtius in the life of Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> Greeke, partly Indian: that of Delphos, where a woman of fifty yeare olde anſwered, ſitting vpon a braſen three-footed ſtoole, in Greeke verſe: that of Latona in Butus a City of Egypt: that of Amphia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raus in <hi>Trophonius</hi> denne: and of late dayes the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that anſwered <hi>Mottenzuma</hi> a King in America: for although at the death of Chriſt, Oracles did ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ceaſe, as appeares by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> yet it is plaine
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21132:49"/> by the ſtorie of <hi>Iulian,</hi> as alſo by <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in his booke of Epſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ta. See Tacitus hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>my. lib. 4.</note> that ſundry particular Oracles did remaine: the Colluſions herein were manifold: firſt the Prieſts often anſwere in ſteade of the Oracle, and ſo ſpake feelingly as men of good gifts. Secondly, the Diuell perſwaded the people, that hee was a God, and ſo commaunded many both cruell Sacrifices, as the offering of men in Scythia, &amp; obſcene cuſtomes, as of <hi>Ceres</hi> in Eleuſis, <hi>Iſis</hi> in Egypt, <hi>Bona Dea</hi> in<note place="margin">Toby Mathewes Sermon on good Friday.</note> Rome: Thirdly, it was pretended that things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were told, when indeed the predictions were doubtfull, that might ſtrike ſayle according to the winde, or were drawne from Nature, as from Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and Aſtrologie, wherein the Diuell is not a little ſeene, as being a ſpirit, and of long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or were taken from the Scripture, as anſweres giuen to <hi>Alexander</hi> concerning his victories, were taken out of the eight of <hi>Daniel;</hi> or laſtly were knowne by ſome commiſſion: thus Sathan might eaſily haue told the deſtruction of <hi>Ahab,</hi> which hee was enioyned to procure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond illuſion in Paganiſme was vſed by Law-giuers, thus <hi>Minos</hi> pretended that he had conference with <hi>Iupiter</hi> about his Lawes, <hi>Solon, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> and <hi>Charondas</hi> with <hi>Apollo, Phalcas</hi> with <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Numa Pompilius</hi> with the Nimph <hi>Aegeria, Diodorus,</hi> and <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo would haue vs beleeue that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21132:49"/> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> vſed the like art in promulgating his lawes, but we haue learned better things: The ground of this fallacy was, that man by nature acknowledging a Deity, is by no obligation ſo firmely bound, as by ſome Religion true or falſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>A Deceit like the former, was much vſed in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of warre, when was deuiſed that Verſe of <hi>Thucidides:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Thucid. lib. 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>Doriacum veniet Loimo comitante duellum.</q>
                  <p>Or in Greeke thus:</p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
                  <p>Some read <hi>Limos,</hi> that is famine and not plague, but the truth is, it was deuiſed after the euent, as ſuch thinges are accuſtomed to be done: ſo <hi>Codrus</hi> king of Athens being ſlaine, the Lacedemonians left the warre of <hi>Attica,</hi> being deceiued by an anſwer, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were forbidden to kill the King of Athens: which thing, as I ſuppoſe, was craftily broac'ht by <hi>Codrus</hi> himſelfe, meaning to die for his Countrie; for the rumour being diuulged abroad, that if the King died, the Lacedemonians ſhould depart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out victory: the King in the habite of a Faggot-car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier entring into the hoaſt, and brawling with a Souldier, was by him ſlaine, who ſtripping him, and finding that he was the King, filled the Armie with a vaine ſuperſtition, whereupon the warre ended. The like is to be found in <hi>Scipio</hi> the elder, at the ſiege
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21132:50"/> of new Carthage in Spaine, who hauing learned by certaine of the Country, that the Riuer had a hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> water about noone, tolde his Souldiers in the morning, that in his dreame he had ſeene <hi>Neptune</hi> ſtanding vpon the water, and promiſing him that he would make it encreaſe about noone, ſo that the boates approaching to the City, they might ſcale and winne it: the Souldiers at noone ſeeing the Riuer to riſe, ſome ſubtile perſons alſo giuing it out, that they ſaw <hi>Neptune</hi> with his three forked mace vpon the Riuer, flew vpon the walles, and tooke the chiefe Citty of Spaine the firſt day of the ſiege. The moſt excellent in this Kind were <hi>Sertorius,</hi> and <hi>Eunes</hi> a bondman: the former kept a tame white Doe, which he made his Souldiers beleeue was <hi>Diana;</hi> by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof he wonne many victories, againſt his Countrey-men the Romanes in Spaine; the other perſwading diuers, that hee had ſpoken with the Goddeſſe of Siria, holding in his mouth certaine<note place="margin">Theſe laſt ſtories are in Juſtin, Liuie, Florus.</note> little Walnut-ſhels with Aqua-vitae in them, did ſeeme to ſpit fire as he ſpake, and ſo wan that credite with many, that he ſtirred vp that great ſeruile war againſt the Romanes. In a word, the greateſt Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of warre, in thoſe dayes, was ſome ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinion bred in the hearts of fooles, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainde by the tongue of the wiſer:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>A Fourth couſenage in Paganiſme, was in Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which they made the people beleeue, could
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21132:50"/> turne their eyes, ſweate, and ſhew many like prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies; the ground was, they thought they could doe miracles, the greateſt part herein was iugling, and deuiſes by hidden Inſtruments; beſides, it is certaine that the Diuell can doe wonders, though not truely miraculous: yea will ſome ſay, but he brought a foure-folde winde vpon the houſe where <hi>Iobs</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren feaſted: We might anſwere, that there is a winde called <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>phias,</hi> wherein three winds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr, which a ſpirit might turne about and make it ſeeme foure; but we anſwere, that indeede it ſtroke the foure corners of the houſe, though it were but one winde, which action though it exceede the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the winde, yet it well agreeth to the naturall force of the Diuel: they adde further that the plague in Egypt came with ſending of euill Angels; ſome<note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 49.</note> ſay, tis meant thus, Meſſengers of euill, meaning <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> but taking it to be meant of Diuels, as it is intimated in the 17. of Wiſd. we ſay, that they may adde terrour, and haſt to the peſtilence, but can not ſend it in an inſtant: what thinke you then (ſay ſome) of men turned into wolues, as <hi>Nabucadonoſer</hi> was into a beaſt, and the daughters of King <hi>Praetus</hi> into Kine? we ſay it was a kind of melancholy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in men thinke themſelues to be beaſts: Againe, we thinke that plague was inflicted vpon <hi>Nabucodonoſer</hi> by God, not by the Diuell. Further they alledge<note place="margin">Matth. 12. 27.</note> the caſting out of Diuels by euill men, but we ſay, eyther they caſt them out by conſent, not by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, or that wicked men may doe miracles, but the Diuell being actualy damned, cannot: laſtly, they
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21132:51"/> adde the things done by the Magitians of Egypt, or to be done by the Beaſt, but theſe are apparitions<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. 13.</note> and not reall.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The Impostures of Turciſme and Iudaijſme.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides Paganiſme there are two other falſe Religions out of the Church: Firſt a great and generall Apoſtacy, then <hi>Iudayſme:</hi> the Apoſtacie was begunne by <hi>Mahomet</hi> one of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Iuglers ſince the creation, he was a Mungrell, borne of an Iſmaelite, and a Iewiſh mother: he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the ſtudy of coniuring tenne yeares, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maried his Miſtreſſe, which was very wealthy, by drunkenneſſe (as it is thought) falling into the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſickenes, when ſhe rebuked him, as if he were a drunken beggar, he meaning that ſhe ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh what he ſayed, intreated her to conceale it: for as a Riuer ſtopped, growes higher aboue the bankes, ſo there is a generation called Women, which being deſired to be ſilent, will tell it more liberally; he told her then to this effect: Haue you not read that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> was ſicke when he ſaw the Angel? It is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel <hi>Gabriel</hi> which appearing to me, thus aſtoniſheth my ſenſes; ſhe promiſed ſilence with her tongue,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21132:51"/> but not for her tongue with her heart: At the next Goſſips meeting, ſhe told them her husband was a Prophet, and ſo from women it went to men: in the meane while <hi>Mahomet</hi> had taught a Doue to picke corne out of his eare, which he ſaid, was the Holy Ghoſt in the likeneſſe of a Doue. About the necke of this Fowle, he put a plate with golden let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to this ſenſe; Let <hi>Mahomet</hi> be King: the ſimple Arabians which had lately reuolted from <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Emperour of Greece, becauſe his Muſter-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter being demaunded paye, had rudely anſwered them, ſaying, we haue not enough for our Greekes and Romanes, and ſhall theſe dogges craue their hyre, immediately elected <hi>Mahomet</hi> their king, who thereupon crauing, as it were from heauen, that he might haue ſome excellent lawes to rule them by, commaunded them to goe into the Wilderneſſe, where ſuddenly a Bull, or (as ſome thinke) an Aſſe came out of a Denne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with a booke of lawes tyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke: This beaſt hee had taught to take bread from his owne hand, and theſe Lawes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">An Hereticke denying the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt. Smithes boooke called Gods ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts.</note> had framed, with the ayde of one <hi>Iohn</hi> a Monk, and <hi>Sergius</hi> a Neſtorian: this booke at this day is called the <hi>Alcheron.</hi> His other prankes I will not recite, as being at large repeated by <hi>Fox, Smith,</hi> and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>ANd as this Sect was bred by fraud, ſo it was fed by deceite, as it may appeare by the poyſoned
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:21132:52"/> doctrine, vomited out in the Alcheron: Firſt, they teach that a man doing good workes, may goe to heauen, of what Religion ſo euer he bee, but euery man muſt deſtroy the aduerſe Sect with fire and ſword to increaſe his owne. The firſt clauſe is the true effect of Atheiſme, the latter doth make them affect all their bloody conqueſts, and therefore at their death they giue Legacies and ſtipends to Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, for the inlarging of the Sect of <hi>Mahomet:</hi> Next they teach, that they pray to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> to commend their Prayers to God, and ſo ſay they, you ſhould do to Chriſt, as being but a holy man, and not God, as was <hi>Mahomet:</hi> this was the deuiſe of <hi>Sergius,</hi> who was a <hi>Neſtorian</hi> as was ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſides they teach <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamie</hi> to bee lawfull, and puniſh Adulterie with death. I know not whether they doe better in the latter, or worſe in the former, but ſure it agrees with reaſon. If a man haue fower wiues, and as many concubines as he can keepe, for ſo much is allowed by that law, if yet hee will commit Adulterie, hee is not worthy to liue. Furthermore, they abhorre Swines fleſh and Bels, the one to pleaſe the Iewes, the other to diſpleaſe the Chriſtians: They allow al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Circumciſion, but in the eight yeere, not on the eight day. Laſtly, Friday is their Sabbaoth, that they might differ both from Iewes and Chriſtians. Thus from a mungrell <hi>Mahomet,</hi> came a mungrell Religion, compil'de of Names, ſhadowes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:21132:52"/>
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>IVdaiſme alſo is tainted with the like errour of Names, for in three things they differ from vs. Firſt, they haue feined ſuch a Meſſias as is beyond all Poetrie, of whom this is the deſcription. <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> ſhall come againe, and prepare for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, he ſhall be a man onely, not God, at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hee ſhall deliuer the Iewes from the power of all Nations, and ſhall bring them to Ieruſalem, which hee ſhall repaire with <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, and there offer ſacrifice, and reſtore all the ceremonies of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Likewiſe, all the fathers ſhall then riſe from the dead, and liue with the Meſſias, who ſhall make a feaſt with the fleſh of <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> which is a kind of great fiſh, wherof onely two were created at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,<note place="margin">See Iob. 40. 41. Chap. And the Iewes vpon them.</note> one preſently killed and ſalted againſt this feaſt, the other to be eaten freſh. This Meſſias ſhall die, after a while the laſt reſurrection ſhalbe, if you ask them of the weekes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> they will agree like the Chaldrons in Dodona, like the Bricklayers of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, or like our common makers of Almanackes, tis no maruaile though it be ſaid, that a Vaile is drawne ouer their heart, otherwiſe it were not poſſible for a man to dote vpon ſuch olde ſicke mens waking dreames: next, they differ in their practiſe of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, by which, they thinke they may vſe vs, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 3. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> did the Aegenets, whoſe right thumbs they cut off, that they might be vnfit to ſayle: they thinke it lawfull for them to take any forfeyture, be it neuer
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21132:53"/> ſo vnequall, any morgage, any pawne, they are not afraid of that wenn which we call <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is vſury vpon vſury, no they dread not to take ten in the hundreth for a weeke: their pretence is, becauſe wee are ſtrangers, as if wee were all Cananites, or ſome of the ſeauen Nations, which were as well to be oppreſt by vſury, as to bee rooted out by <hi>Ioſuah:</hi> and marke this in them, that whereas in ancient time Publicans and Sinners were counted as all one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, now themſelues are the Publicans or Tole-gatherers of the great Turke: Laſtly, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Polygamie aſwell as the Turkes, but are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed vpon the eight day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>THeir practiſes are no leſſe entangled with error then their doctrine, for, firſt they deuiſed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">Et quicquid Graecia men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>det in hiſtorij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Iuuenal Sat. 6.</note> books of Tradition, called the <hi>Talmud</hi> and the <hi>Chabala,</hi> wherein are more lies then in <hi>Lucians</hi> true ſtory, more then euer the Grecians deuiſed, and yet theſe are ſo obſtinately maintained, that if any of their Children ſhall but incline to heare our reaſons and bookes, they will not ſticke to hurle them into hote furnaces: Againe, they haue ſuch an inuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate hatred againſt Chriſt, that in contempt of him they will crucifie Children vpon Good-friday: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if the husband or wife turne Chriſtian, the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayſing party maryeth another. Laſtly, their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous skill in wreſting places from vs by falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21132:53"/> as it can bee aſcribed to no other thing then their endleſſe diligence (for they haue ſet downe how many letters and points there bee in the Bible, and how oft each is repeated, yea, many of them can recite the whole context without booke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) ſo it is a great cauſe of their obſtinacy, which is alſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med partly by our ignorance, partly by our diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>NEyther may wee thinke, that onely circumciſed perſons are Turkes and Iewes, many with vs baptized maintaine both Sects in their liues. The Turkes thinke a man may bee ſaued in any Religion with good workes, and haue not wee men at their death that are to chuſe their Religion? Doe not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinke they may be ſaued, though they liue as ill as hee, that determines neuer to repent till hee die, though they eate as if they ſhould die to morrow, and build as if they ſhould liue for euer? The Turkes denie the three perſons, and we beleeue them not, becauſe we know them not: they hold <hi>Polygamie,</hi> but puniſh Adulterie, we the contrarie. The Iewiſh vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, malice, and lying, <hi>iam gentilitate ſunt donata,</hi> they are become Gentlemen, <hi>O vngentle gentiles.</hi> Is not this to harden the Iewe, and to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> awake the drowſie trumpe of the Turke? either liue according to your Baptiſme, or elſe be Circumciſed: If you would but keepe your words as well as they, wee would not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21132:54"/> complaine of your deedes, but were Iuſtice as ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with you as with them, wee would ſay, <hi>redeunt Saturnia ſaecla.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The Dreames of the Graecians.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reece the Epitome of the World, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of Greece, ſo it was in ancient time, but now it is the ſlaue of ſlaues. The wild Boare hath entred into her Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. The Turke in the great Temple of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, tyes Lyons and Beares, and other wilde beaſts, which he feedes with the fleſh of the Greekes and other Chriſtians. Their children are Tithed to bee his Vaſſals and Ianizaries, which afterwards proue the moſt ſauage enemies to their Countrey, the reſt are forbidden to learne liberall Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as <hi>Iulian</hi> alſo forbad the Chriſtians. Their daughters are taken to be Concubines to the Turke, all ancient Lawes, diuine and humane, are now brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the will of a Barbarian: the moſt wiſe, wittie, actiue Nation in the world, is ſubiect to the moſt cruell, vnlearned, vntractable, and vnfatiable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement. Where be now the Oliues of Athens, the Swans of Thebes, the pleaſures of double Sea'd
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21132:54"/> Corinthus, the liberties of Laconia? Where be the houſes of <hi>Elis,</hi> the horſemen of Theſſalia, the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Macedon? Where be the Palmes of <hi>Epirus</hi> now cal'd <hi>Albania?</hi> My belly my belly, I am pained with griefe, the famous Nation, ſpectacle of all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where were the ſeuen golden Candleſticks, to which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote, now is in the yron Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,<note place="margin">Fellonia eſt quod ſit animo fellio. Bracton.</note> and ſerues in Bricke and Clay, vnder a farre more fierce, fell, and fellonious <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THe cauſe of this wofull miſerie reſteth to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, ſome ſay it was becauſe the Greeke Church brake downe Images, other becauſe they could neuer indure the Popes ſupremacie: Others that becauſe in the dayes of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth, they reuolted from the Latine Church, but theſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">According to the prouerbe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>uas.</note> ſmell too much of the Bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loniſh Brickes, which all the water in Tybris cannot make white and ſweete: Some aſcribe it to the iarres and broyles betwene the brethren, about the Empire of Greece: Some haue accuſed <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing the Imperiall ſeate from Rome to Bizance now called Conſtantinople: As alſo for disfurniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Europe of their ordinarie Legions, by which each Border was kept from inuaſion, theſe cauſes are true, but they are too low. Phiſicke ſaith, that all rhume comes from the crowne of the head, ſo ſay we, all trouble in a Nation comes from ſome ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21132:55"/> in the head, this Church and people alwaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">Auſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ad Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> were full of fancies and hereſies, within fower hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeeres after Chriſt, there were noted eightie ſeuerall hereſies in that Countrey, but euen at this day their Dreames are many, though their troubles be not Dreames; but their Dreames are theſe: Firſt, they will not worſhip Images, leaſt they ſhould ſeeme to agree with the Romane Church, and yet they will adore Pictures: This is not vnlike certaine<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ro pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o.</note> pleaſant men in <hi>Suetonius,</hi> who would ſeale bonds, thus, <hi>Caio Caeſare &amp; Iulio Caeſare conſulibus,</hi> whereas <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Iulius Caeſar</hi> was but one man. But <hi>Bibulus</hi> his fellow Conſul was counted a gull, and a Cypher according to the Verſes.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conſule ſub Caio factum hoc &amp; Caeſare nuper,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nam Bibulo factum Conſule nil memini.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This done, <hi>Caius</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> Conſuls were,</l>
                     <l>For vnder <hi>Bibulus</hi> nought done we heare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>So theſe men know no Idoll called an Image, but<note place="margin">An Epistle of Epiphanius tranſlated by Jerom.</note> yet they runne a whoring after idle Pictures: when <hi>Epiphanius</hi> rebuked the Vaile at Anablatha, becauſe it had onely the figure of a man vpon it, thinke wee that Images and Pictures did not ſeeme equally idle Idols vnto him?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>ANother dreame of the Grecians is, that they acknowledge the proceeding of the holy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:21132:55"/> Ghoſt from the Father, but not from the Sonne: their Bulwarke is a Bul-ruſh, their ſtaffe is a ſtaffe ofreede, which who ſo leaneth on ſhall fall, and the Cane ſhall runne into his ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d: but what thinke<note place="margin">If Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ſeuenth bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke of naturall hiſtorie.</note> you is their defence? trickes of Philoſophy, which are like the lances of the Pigmies: ti's ſaide that <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docles</hi> was burnt in Aetna, whileſt he curiouſly inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the myſteries thereof. Oh, but this is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mountaine of fire, this is higher then the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Alpes, then Caucaſus, then Paropaniſus; high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then Mount Picus, nay higher then the heauen of heauens: this mountaine burneth more then Aetna, then Veſuuius, then Hybla, nay then Hell it ſelfe; if men dare ſo preſumptuouſly looke aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſt the Sunne, that are no Eagles: it is ſaide when <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> was writing of the Trinitie, he ſaw by the ſea ſide a Childe digging a little hole in the ground, and taking water with a ſpoone out of the ſea, to poure into this hole, the childe being demaunded why he ſo did, anſwered he would lade the whole ſea into it; hee replyed, the ſea is too great, the hole, the ſpoon, and thou too little; to whome the childe anſwered, ſo art thou vnable to write of the Trinity, and ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht: but I feare my waxen winges will burne, if I flie too neare this glorious Sunne, and therefore I leaue the Grecians to their Phauloſophie.<note place="margin">Eui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l wiſedome</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>A Third Greekiſh dreame which keepes them ſtill in their Lethargie, as if they ſlept vpon a bed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:21132:56"/> of Mandrakes, or had eaten the graines of <hi>Requies ſancti Nicholai,</hi> which Saint the Greekes ſo much<note place="margin">Eſpecially in Ruſſia.</note> worſhippe: this dreame I ſay is, that they read their Liturgies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: ſtrange tongues to diuers of their Churches: In Ruſſia at this day they read the Bible in Slauonian, which the common people vnderſtand not: ſo the Iewes reade in Hebrew, whereof many thouſands of that Nation know not a word, what is this but to plucke out <hi>Sampſons</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, &amp; to make him grinde and play vpon a Harpe: we haue a fable that the Dragon fighting with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, pluckes out his eyes, and ſo ſeazeth vpon him: the eye of the people is Gods word, which if it bee read in a ſtrange tongue, is like the eye of <hi>Pentheus</hi> when hee was mad, who thought as <hi>Virgill</hi> ſayth,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et geminum Solem, &amp; duplices ſe oſtendere Thebas:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is a famine like that of <hi>Tantalus, Semper eget li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Metamor. lib. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſemper abundat aquis,</hi> or like that of <hi>Narciſſus, Exigua prohibemur aqua:</hi> for this people dayly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Bible, and yet knoweth it not, and are like thoſe men which were with <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaw the light, and heard the ſound, but neither ſaw the perſon, nor vnderſtood the voyce, or like the thirſty glutton in Hell, who ſaw <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome: theſe politicke Churchmen are like <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> who inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Empire, firſt made ſure of Alexandria, where were all the Garners of Rome, that he might make the Romanes yeeld for feare of famine: theſe men foreſtall the bread of God from the people, but<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 26.</note> the people ſhall curſe them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:21132:56"/>
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>HEre I may take vp the complaint, which <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbeg</hi> the King of Albania did vſe in his life time, which was that Kings of Europe did not agree to that ouerthrow of the Turks, which agreement howſoeuer it ſound ill in the eares of Polititians, who remember the ſaying of <hi>Scipio Naſica,</hi> that if Carthage were deſtroyed, the Romanes ſhould haue ciuill warres, the verity of which ſpeech was confirmed by <hi>Scylla, Marius,</hi> and other firebrands of the State, yet without queſtion, it is not alone to be imputed, to theſe and other ſuch deuiſes of men, but partly to our iniquities, which make vs partly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to ſo noble an enterpriſe, as killing the Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manthean Boare by <hi>Hercules, Calidonian</hi> by <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ager,</hi> the <hi>Tarentine</hi> by <hi>Piſistratus;</hi> partly to theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting dreames of the Grecians themſelues, out of which they cannot yet be awaked by the ſhrill trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of wofull warre, and the yron whippes of long and loathſome ſeruitude, but ſtill they ſleepe on both eares, as if they had taken <hi>Ladanum Paracelſi,</hi> to be made Eunuches before they wake; well, <hi>proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ardet Eucalegon,</hi> our wall is the next, and it is to bee feared, that Greekiſh lying errors, drunkenneſſe, inconſtancie grow both rife among vs, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nouriſhed, by how much wee exceede them in wealth, peace and liberty: the Iewes that were Gods people, are now runnagates for all their boaſts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Greekes that haue beene Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21132:57"/> are now bond-men, for all their boaſts of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: theſe patternes are penſiled out to vs, not that we ſhould inſult ouer their preſent, but conſult a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our owne ſuture miſerie, and learne by their dreadfull and cruell yoake, to beware of the lees of lazineſſe, and the lyes of hereſies, and not to ſuffer <hi>Cadmus</hi> or <hi>Iaſon</hi> to ſowe the Dragons teeth in our land: that is, the ſubtile ſeedes of endleſſe enuie and reſtleſſe contention.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> The Wolfe of Romulus.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Omulus</hi> and <hi>Remus</hi> as the Fable goes,<note place="margin">Dlutarch in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Dion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſius Halicarnaſſeus. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rgil in the and of the 8. booke of his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neid.</note> were nouriſht by a ſhee Wolfe, indeede by <hi>Laurentia</hi> the wife of <hi>Fauſtulus,</hi> which woman obtainde this worthy Title for her vnchaſte and cruell behauiour: certes, what ſhe was I know not, but this I am ſure of, that her elder nurſling <hi>Romulus,</hi> could howle as well as any Wolfe in Arcadia: yea and both robbe and kill, as appeares by the murthering of his brother <hi>Remus</hi> and king <hi>Tatius,</hi> by the erecting the <hi>Aſilum</hi> and Sanctuary for all that were in debt, in bondage, or in want, though they were as badde as he, of whom it <note place="margin">Iuuenal. Sat. 4.</note> is ſaid <hi>Monſtrum nulla virtute redemptum—A vitijs:</hi>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:21132:57"/> as alſo by the ſtealing of the Sabine women, for which, and other like Woluiſh deedes he was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away in a tempeſt by the King of Lycaonia, I<note place="margin">VVo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and. Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n his booke de Sort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arys.</note> meane the Prince of darkeneſſe, for ſo <hi>Danaeus</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth; howſoeuer <hi>Proculus</hi> ſware that he ſaw him like a God. But to leaue him tormented where hee is, howſoeuer we praiſe him, where he is not, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes his ſucceſſors, would neuer leaue his Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh nature: the Kings, Conſuls, Emperours, did howle and prey ſo well, that no Princes in the earth which are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhepheards of the people could ſaue their fleecie flockes from their all-deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring teeth, but after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> went to Byzance, <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſter</hi> and his ſucceſſors, <hi>Boniface</hi> the third and the eight, <hi>Zacharie, Alexander, Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth and ninth, with others, did finde ſuch meanes, that they made <hi>Charlemaine</hi> Emperour, ouercame the Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, got <hi>Rauenna</hi> from the Emperour of Greece, after changed the Empire to <hi>Otho</hi> the great, and in concluſion, trodde vpon the necke of <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, and gotte the Emperour to be choſen by the ſeuen Electors, thus ſet downe in theſe verſes:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Maguntinenſis, Treuerenſis, Colonienſis,</l>
                     <l>Et Palatinus dapifer, Dux Potiferencis,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Marchio praepoſitus Camerae, pincerna Bohemus.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Since which time the Turke hath alwaies incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Antiquili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> into Europe, like the Sea, that plucked <hi>Pharos</hi> from Egypt, Sicily from Italy, England from Fraunce.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:21132:58"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>BEſides theſe Woluiſh deuiſes, all ſealed with the Fiſhers Ring, they haue found Lime-twigges to catch men, ſpecially if they be purſie and fatte, to reckon all were endleſſe, I will name ſome few, that you may know the birds by their neaſts: firſt, they haue ſet vp a great Kitchin, full of Grydirons and Caldrons to broyle and boile ſoules in, out of which none can eſcape, except he pay to the Maſter-Cooke great ſtore of <hi>Vnguentum Album,</hi> that they may ſay a <hi>Requiem</hi> for his ſoule: this Kitchin is like an Iron-Mill, which conſumes all the wood in the Countrey, or like the table of <hi>Vitellius,</hi> or <hi>Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus:</hi> in this they burne all the Straw and Hay, for ſo they call their veniall ſinnes, for which they get ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, gold, and pretious ſtones: If a man ſhould aske them how they know it, if you be an ignorant man, it may be they will trouble you with a Scripture or <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 12.</note> two, otherwiſe they will bring an olde mooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten booke out of a darke corner, called Traditions and another out of a darker then that, called the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends and viſions of Saints; and with theſe Fables, worſe then <hi>Eſops</hi> or <hi>Ouids,</hi> they make the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thoſe things, which themſelues deride.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>AVricular confeſſion is another Lime-twigge, or rather a hooke euen to catch <hi>Leuiathan</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21132:58"/> for by this tricke they haue ſearched out, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all Princes and States, and few forts of Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity haue beene found ſtronge enough to keepe out theſe bold and cunning Scalers. <hi>Hanibal</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended much, becauſe he knew the ſecrets of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, but had he had a fewe Counceilers of this packe, he would haue found himſelfe to haue beene but a nouice. It was ſaid of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> that he was <hi>Omnium faeminarum vir, omnium virorum faemina:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Suetonius in Julio.</note> which ſpeach, though it be literally true of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, yet it may be another way interpreted of them in this manner; that of all perſons that ſeeme to be weake as women, they are moſt manly and potent by the meanes of this confeſſion, and yet of all that pretend ſecreſie like men, they are the moſt open tongued (I had almoſt ſaid womaniſh) that may be; for by this deuiſe there is no <hi>Mars</hi> but they will take him in a net, no <hi>Pharaohs</hi> chamber in which they will not croke like the Frogges of Egypt: And to conclude, they are as skilfull in the planet of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> as <hi>Ptolomie</hi> or <hi>Alfragan,</hi> but in a worſe ſenſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>A Third deuiſe is in their Images, Pilgrimages and Saints: this fetch doth get as much as <hi>Bells</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage did eate, and of affinitie to theſe are their Iube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, which they like good <hi>Cronologers, Meton, Calippus</hi> and others, haue varied in diuers periods, drawing it
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:21132:59"/> from the hundreth to the fiftieth, I to the fiue and<note place="margin">Read S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ger d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> temporam and vpon E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bius.</note> twentieth yeare, not vnlike <hi>Claudius Caeſar,</hi> who ſet out the playes called Saeculares, which by cuſtome were kept euery hundreth yeare, when as many, that were not fiftie yeare old, had ſeene the former playes in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> time; ſo that the Cryer could not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Proclamation almoſt for laughter. Not all the Nauigations into Weſt India, were euer ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to Spaine, as theſe pollicies haue beene to the keeper of Tybris Bridge: whence his name <hi>Pontifex</hi> in part is drawne. The ground of all theſe is in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, Bulles, Indulgences, things more attractiue of golde, then the load-ſtone of Iron, then Amber or Iette of ſtraw; to theſe we may adde the Cruciats, whereby pardon is promiſed them, that will fight for the recouerie of the holy land, by theſe hee hath drawne many Emperours and Princes out of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, which otherwiſe ſhould haue had both time and power to haue bridled him: he hath alſo found meanes in their abſence, that their Countries ſhould be inuaded, and he receiue the gaine of the warre. By theſe and the like Stratagems<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pope John.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> the three and twentieth left behinde him fiue and twenty mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Duckets, and <hi>Boneface</hi> the eight had as much treaſure taken from him by a French Captaine, as would ſatisfie all the Princes of Europe for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes a whole yeare: what ſhall I ſay of the fortie thouſand pounds, for the tolleration of ſtewes year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Jn his booke iayned to that de Hereſibus.</note> taken? He that will know more, may reade <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:21132:59"/>
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>ANother Arttificiall fire, is the name of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, which hatcheth forth ſo many orders, that they ſeeme to ſwarme like Locuſts, of all which the lateſt ſet vp by <hi>Ignatius Laiola,</hi> who turned Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans into Ieſuites, and as one ſaid <hi>Ieſuitas in Suitas</hi> hath<note place="margin">A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Idololat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra.</note> ſurpaſt all the reſt, not onely in ſtrictneſſe of vowes, namely ſingle life, wilfull pouertie, regular obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but eſpecially in diligence, and that of diuers ſorts: firſt Arts and tongues, heretofore buried in the graue of idleneſſe, now by induſtry they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued, neyther haue they neglected Hiſtorie, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humanity, next they haue beene diligent in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, a thing before <hi>Luther</hi> vnknowne in that Church. Beſides, they haue refined all their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that they were almoſt filed away: the neweſt Poperie then is ſcarce ſo olde as the comming in of Beere. Furthermore, theſe diligent blood-hounds, by their endleſſe intelligences, which they haue in each Countrey, by their Artes of ſetling and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as they call them, by their Inquiſition procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a hot burning zeale, haue wondrouſly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to repaire their ruines, ſo long foretolde and now begunne, they ſee what Countries haue reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from them, all Great Britane, with Ireland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, Swethland, and Norway, great part of France with both Germanies, Bohemia, Poland, Hungary, nay they ſee themſelues bearded in Italy, not only by the Venetians that euer ſuſpected them, but euen by
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:21132:60"/> their beſt friends Millan and Naples. We ſay that wild beaſts when they are ready to die, bite moſt fiercely: So doe theſe Wolues, ſeeing this great Earthquake in their eſtate, among other things, they<note place="margin">Apoc. 11. 13.</note> haue locked vp the Bible in a ſtrange tongue from the people, herein ſurpaſſing the Iewes and Ruſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, for they reade the Scriptures onely in a ſtrange <hi>dialect,</hi> but theſe in a language that hath no affinitie to the mother tongue. To conclude,</p>
                  <q>Qui cum Ieſu itis, ne itis cum Ieſuitis.</q>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. VI.</head>
                  <p>THe laſt, but no wayes the leaſt Policie, is a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, farre beyond <hi>Heliodore, Apollodore,</hi> or Sir <hi>Philips Muſidore,</hi> it is the deſcription of Antichriſt, the maner whereof is this in effect. There ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe a man, begot by the Diuell of a woman, which ſhall be of the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> but this man ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that he is a Iewe and the Iewes Meſſias, he ſhall reigne three yeeres and a halfe, hee ſhall fight with <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> hee ſhall bring downe fire from heauen, he ſhall put downe Maſſe and openly bee of no Religion, but ſecretly worſhip the Diuell called <hi>Mauzzim,</hi> he ſhall kill <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> which ſhall come out of Paradiſe to fight againſt him, whoſe bodies ſhall be left vnburied three dayes and a halfe: He ſhall reigne in Ieruſalem, and fortie fiue dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, the day of iudgement ſhall be. This is their Antichriſt, a thing ſtranger then the Crocodils
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:21132:60"/> of Nilus, then all the rare things of Arenoque or Guianoque, riuers in America: But becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in proſe expreſſe it, you ſhall heare the tenth Muſe her ſelfe, vtter it in her owne language thus,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A thing more ſtrange, then on Niles ſlime the Sunne</l>
                     <l>Ere bred, or all which into <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke came:<note place="margin">Dunne in his Satyres.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>A thing which would haue poſed <hi>Adam</hi> to name,</l>
                     <l>Stranger then the ſeuen Antiquaries ſtudies.</l>
                     <l>Then Affricks monſters, Guyanes rarities,</l>
                     <l>Stranger then ſtrangers.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>This Antichriſt is moſt poetically figured alſo by the famous heire Apparant to <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Virgil,</hi> in his <hi>Faiery Queene</hi> vnder the names of <hi>Archimagus, Dueſſa, Argoglio</hi> the Soldane and others, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note place="margin">Saunders eight Booke de viſibili Monarchia. Bellarmine 3. booke, De ſummo P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atifice.</note> the firſt and fift Legends. If any man doubt whether this fiction of Antichriſt be general among them, let him conſult with the principall Wolues, who haue howled lowdeſt in this matter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The reſurrection of Hereſie.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reſurrection, as other myſteries of the Goſpel, was heard of among the Heathens by a kind of tradition: But as Fame and waters, the further they goe, the more they are corrupted: So
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:21132:61"/> theſe traditions iſſuing from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he true fountaine of trueth, when they came into the Copper-mines and muddy channels of the Heathens, were made bitter and vnpure. Among the reſt, the Egyptians, <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herodotus in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>terpe. For Pythagoras, ſee Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stotle. Lucian. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d.</note> and <hi>Herod</hi> in the Goſpel, did dreame of a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Soules from body to body, which wee call <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, by which as many thinke, the Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was darkely and corruptly intimated. Wee reade in the Scriptures, that <hi>Iohn</hi> came in the ſpirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> and ſo I thinke by the contrary, many perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Heretickes of our time, are led with the ſame ſpirit of the Diuel, which was in <hi>Simon Magus, Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus, Ebion, Arius, Samoſatenus,</hi> ſo that it may ſeeme, that as <hi>Proteſilaus</hi> obtained leaue of <hi>Pluto</hi> to ſee <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimia:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Claudian de raptu Proſer.</note> So theſe men for a time haue got licence to reuiſite the earth. Tis ſaid in <hi>Claudian</hi> when <hi>Pluto</hi> married <hi>Proſerpina, Ixion, Siſiphus, Tantalus, Tyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and the <hi>Belides</hi> made holy day, and the like Tale is told of our Lady comming to Purgatorie: for there is but a Wanſcot betweene it and Hell, and the fire in them both, is all of one ſubſtance, onely the one<note place="margin">Arius, a Priest in the Church of Alexandria, Anno 320.</note> is temporall, the other euerlaſting: But howſoeuer theſe Tales be, both the Germaine and Tranſiluania can tell you truely, that they haue many that follow that doctrine of <hi>Arius,</hi> denying Chriſts diuinitie: and if you tell them that hee voided his bowels, as hee ſhould haue done his excrements, and that this<note place="margin">Caluin in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.</note> befell him at the Prayer of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> they will not ſticke to deride you, and call <hi>Athanaſius</hi> heretick, yea, and to condemne the whole Church. <hi>Seruetus</hi> one<note place="margin">Bellarmine in his booke De Trinitate.</note> of this crew was not afraid to cal the Trinitie a three headed <hi>Cerberus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:21132:61"/>
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THe cauſe and remedy of theſe prodigies is harde to find, as it was ſaide of the Allobrogians, t'was harder to finde them out, then to ouercome them: the cauſe therefore, or rather the occaſion was this, men deſiring to reforme the Romiſh Synagogue in all points, thought with the Hermites friend to caſt away the whole apple, becauſe part of it was rotten: ſo theſe men ſeeing other points to be doubtfully, or dangerouſly ſet downe, ſuſpected alſo the doctrine of the Trinity.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>En quo diſcordia Ciues—</l>
                     <l>Perduxit miſeros, en queis conſeuimus agros,</l>
                     <l>Barbarus haec tam culta noualia miles habebit?</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The remedy is a generall Councell, which now may not be hoped for, the Churches of Greece cannot come, as being oppreſt by the Turke, they of Italie and Spaine will not come, knowing they cannot be parties, except they be Iudges: they that are in France Germany, England dare not come, remembring the infidelity at the Councell of <hi>Constance,</hi> where <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of Prage were burned, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Emperours ſafe conduct, as alſo their inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient<note place="margin">Reade Gentilet about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> dealing at the Councell of Trent. To this may be added, that theſe Heretikes themſelues doe reiect alſo Councels, Fathers, Antiquity, wherein they ſhow themſelues to be more wilfull, then the olde Arrians, who neither at, nor after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Arimine, refuſed any ſuch triall. Laſtly, the ſluggiſhneſſe of Magiſtrates, a maine remedie for
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:21132:62"/> this malady, is much to bee complayned of, for theſe men will not compel the gueſts to come to the feaſt, theſe follow neither the example of the Iewiſh Kings, as <hi>Ezekiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſias,</hi> nor of the heatheniſh <hi>Nabuchodonozer</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> the Mede nor of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and others, who compelled the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes to renounce their blaſphemies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>AN other maine cheriſhing cauſe of theſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, is our ignorance and contradiction in our<note place="margin">See Zanchiuz contra quendam Arianum. Parſons in his booke of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation.</note> interpretation of places concerning the Trinity, this appeareth by the obiections, wherwith they choake vs out of our owne Writers, the tree in Aeſope was moſt ſorry, becauſe it was torne with wedges made out of her owne body; ſo wee are moſt wounded with our owne weapons; many of our Authors writing rather to confute others, then to confeſſe<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See Remiſts vpon Ioh. 1. and Bellarmine in the beginning of the booke</hi> De Trinitate, <hi>and Danaeus vpon him.</hi>
                     </note> the truth, and yet the ſlaunders of diuers men are intollerable: the effect of theſe errors is moſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall, for the Turkes whoſe maine hereſie is Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, are hereby made moſt obſtinate, not onely in their barbarous opinions, but euen in their warres, who in their ſauage manner of proceeding doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the Gothes, Hunnes, Vandals, and Lumbards.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:21132:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Frenzie with many heades.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eryon</hi> for his three bodies, <hi>Chimaera</hi> for her three faces, <hi>Cerberus</hi> for his three, and <hi>Hydra</hi> for her fifty heades, are moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Poets: but this age hath brought forth a Monſter, which for number of heades, ſting, &amp; poyſon, hath been moſt miraculous, their names are more then the names of Diuelles in Agrippa, names that would haue poſed <hi>Cyrus, Simonides, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> and <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> to haue remembred: the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall name is Anabaptiſts, wee call them the <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> in the Law Countries there bee two and thirty ſects of them, which like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes are tyed by the tayles, but differ in their heads and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, they all agree in this, to fire the Church, and yet each man contends for his owne Sect: Like as men that fight at ſea with fire and ſword, waſting each other, till at the length a ſtorme ariſeth which caſteth away both ſides.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>TO name their opinions were to deſire the life of <hi>Methuſalath,</hi> for a man may be thirty yeares of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:21132:63"/> their ſect, and yet not know the Tyth of their do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine, yet the maine pointes are theſe; firſt, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue no ſtory of the Bible, if you take it literally; for they take the Serpent to be nothing but mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, <hi>Eue</hi> the affection, <hi>Adam</hi> reaſon aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to it: the Virgine <hi>Marie</hi> they interprete righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and euery man perfectly regenerated, is a very Chriſt: nay, they are notable Critickes, for they teach their Nouices the Etimologies of all names in the Bible, for example, thus, <hi>Caine</hi> ſlew <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> that is, Poſſeſſion ſlew Vanity: And many Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories they frame hence, like the webs of Spiders, inſomuch as they ſay, there ſhall be no reſurrection of the body, but only a riſing from ſinne, there is no holy Ghoſt but onely good thoughtes: this coine<note place="margin">Acts. 23. 8</note> they borrowed from the Saduces: againe, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Magiſtrates, and warre, and going to law, all ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of oathes, all property of goodes or wiues, therein going beyond <hi>Plato,</hi> who held all thinges ſhould be common, but wiues; who therein (as one ſaid) was contrary to many Cities, where nothing is common but women: alſo they rebaptize men bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by Heretickes, and they dreame that men Dei-fide, and Elders illuminated as they terme them, muſt be taught by Reuelation not by Scriptures: from the former opinion they are called Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,<note place="margin">Reade of theſe matters in Prateolus. Knox. Knewſtubs, Bateman his booke of the leaden Gods.</note> from the latter, Enthuſiaſts: and to conclude this, they imagine all nations ſhall one day bee of their ſect: thinke you that <hi>Endimion</hi> did euer dreame ſuch dreames, or the ſeauen ſleepers that ſlept from the times of <hi>Decius</hi> to the dayes of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> but
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:21132:63"/> what will not Noueltie and Singularity bring foorth?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THere is yet a peculiar faction of this litter, the moſt deformed and prodigious that euer was heard of: It is the faction of the Libertines, ſet vp by <hi>Coppin</hi> and <hi>Quintan,</hi> two baſe perſons in the Low-Countries, whoſe ſtory you may read in <hi>Bellarmine:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bellarm. lib. 2. de peccato.</note> the ſumme of their opinion is, That ſinne is nothing but ſcruple of conſcience, for euery man (ſay they) may liue as the ſpirit moues him, and regeneration with them is nothing but a minde freed from feare of ſinning: I thinke a great cauſe of theſe errours, hath beene the ſuppoſition, that heauen is nothing but a good conſcience, and hell a badde. Now a good conſcience they expound to be, a minde voide of care, a badde the contrary: doe we dreame or are we awake? is it poſſible that men ſhould thus plaie with edge tooles? there were among<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Philoſophers two hundreth eightie eight ſects <hi>de Summo bono,</hi> but theſe men are worſe then thoſe that built Babel, they haue not found out newe tongues but new Dialects, or rather the ſordid language of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Cheaters.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:21132:64"/>
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>NEyther hath our own Countrie been free from this vermin, there was one <hi>Hacket</hi> executed for this ſect, who gaue it out publiquely, that he was Chriſt, he had two fore-runners, the one of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other of mercy, <hi>Coppinger</hi> and <hi>Ardenton:</hi> twas thought hee dealt by Sorcery: ſure I am, hee dealt by the enemie of mankind, hee himſelfe died blaſphemouſly: <hi>Coppinger</hi> hearing of his death, knockt out his owne braines, as it is ſaid, for griefe, that he had beene ſo bewitched by him. We reade of a bond-man, that pretended he was <hi>Agrippa</hi> the nephew of <hi>Augustus,</hi> and being brought to <hi>Tyberius,</hi> and demanded how he came to be <hi>Agrippa,</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as thou cameſt to be <hi>Tyberius:</hi> the like impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy we reade of <hi>Perkin Warebeck</hi> here in England. But with what braſſe (do you thinke) was his fore-head<note place="margin">Hacke.</note> armde, that in this light of knowledge in the mother Citty of this land, in the moſt open place thereof, durſtpubliſh himſelfe to be Chriſt? To end this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I take it we are to be taught hereby, that wee neuer can be ſecure, if we truſt in our owne ſtrength: this man had all the priuiledges from falling that might be, and yet when the raine, the winde, the floods came, it appeared hee was built vpon Sand, wherefore let vs not ſo much contemne his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as condemne our owne imbecility.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:21132:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> The Viper of Schiſme.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a Fable that the yong Vipers eate out the ſides of their damme, this to bee a fable, <hi>Geſner</hi> ſheweth, proouing the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to bee nothing elſe but the Engliſh Adder. But whatſoeuer become of this fable, ſure it is, that we haue ſtore of Sciſmatickes, which doe truely eate out the ſides of the Church their mother: and firſt for their name, there is ſome doubt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayes of one:</p>
                  <q>Matre Paleſtina, dubio genitore creatus.</q>
                  <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tamor. 5.</note>
                  <p>So the mother of theſe, namely madam Pride we know, but <hi>Browne</hi> of whom they were firſt called Browniſts, as himſelfe refuſeth the Name, ſo is hee by them reiected: Some therefore father it vpon him, that was wont to ſpit at the name of an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, as people were wont to doe when they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med<note place="margin">Barrowe.</note> the foule thiefe, and others commend him that ſaid, what thou doſt, doe quickly: And thereupon bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g demaunded, why hee compared himſelfe to Chriſt, he anſwered, not my ſelfe to Chriſt, but you<note place="margin">Green<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wood.</note> to <hi>Iudas.</hi> Some of theſe charitable ſpirited fathers, may iuſtly haue this Baſtard imputed to them, and I
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:21132:65"/> know not whether ſome that haue reuolted from them, may not ſtill bee charged with keeping of the child. For one of them being being demanded, why hee kept a Liuing in our Church, anſwered, hee wiſht that he had a hundred, for the Iſraelites might robbe the Egyptians. This charitie was as hotte as Hell fire, and therefore he that had it, may be iuſtly Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop among them, if hee will not ſpit at this name aſwell as his fellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>THeir opinions are like the Element of fire,<note place="margin">Aſlacus de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicicaelo.</note> which is <hi>exceſſus feruoris.</hi> But as <hi>Aſlacus</hi> intends to proue this fire to bee no Element, ſo I thinke this feruor may be proued to be no Religion, proceeding neither from Prudence, Charitie, nor veritie: They thinke firſt Biſhops to bee Antichriſtian with all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Officers: Secondly, Miniſters by them elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be Apoſtaticall not Apoſtolicall: Thirdly, the Church, becauſe it is compounded of ſo many open euill liuers to be an Adultreſſe. Fourthly, ſet Prayer to bee Swines fleſh, yea though we ſay the Lords Prayer, for as they fancie, this is a paterne of Prayer, not a Prayer, and ſo <hi>Greenewoode</hi> anſwereth to that<note place="margin">Numb. 6. 23.</note> place in <hi>Numbers.</hi> Fiftly, they call ſinging of Pſalmes in the Church, howling of Wolues, croking of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens: And ſixtly, they will neither bee iudged by a Biſhoppe nor by Elders, but by popular ſuffrages and voices, hating Monarchy as Tyranny, for which
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:21132:65"/> they call our Church no Church, and <hi>Ariſtocracie</hi> as<note place="margin">See the Epiſtles of Junius to them of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dam.</note> 
                     <hi>Oligarchy,</hi> for which reaſon they terme the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches bad Churches, they leane rather to a forme of <hi>Democracie</hi> or <hi>Ochlocracie,</hi> wherin the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and heedleſſe multitude Steeres the Helme, I thinke as wiſely as <hi>Palinurus</hi> when hee was ſleepie. Seuenthly, they hold that Vniuerſities and Degrees ſhould be aboliſht, and no maruaile, for they deſire the Study of Arts, and tongues were caſt away.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THeir diſordered practiſe is little wondered at by wiſemen, becauſe they ſee it doeth neceſſarily flow from their Lunaticke opinions, yet it is pitied by good men, derided by bad. Why? will you ſay, may not a man laugh at theſe follies compounded of pride, ignorance, and contention, as the man at Venice ſaid: Gunpowder was made of Salt-peter, Brimſtone and Cole. I anſwere, were not the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanite in the Land, this contention might be borne with, or derided: But while theſe men play the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels on the Stage, many times there comes a Diuell more then tale. Publike enemies come in, whileſt we regard not ciuill mutinies: therefore <hi>Heraclitus</hi> teares, are here farre more ſeemely then <hi>Democritus</hi> laughter. To returne to their practiſe, it is a maner of Propheſie as they terme it, wherein diuers of the ancient priuate men doe publikely expound Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Paſtor himſelfe concluding the exerciſe,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:21132:66"/> this was alſo practiſed in the reformed Churches ſome few yeares agoe, but now they relinquiſh it, ſinding it to bee obnoxius to error, and alteration: but theſe men obſtinately retaine it, and indeed their franticke opinions were more tollerable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were it not for their contumacy and vncharitable cenſures, wherwith they rend vs as with horſes and thornes,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as it was ſaid of <hi>Metius Suffetius:</hi> is it not ſtrange that a brother ſhould excommunicate a brother, that a man ſhould caſt his owne Father out of the church? wee reade that <hi>Marcion</hi> the Heretique was excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by his owne Father, but a like madneſſe to this we neuer read; alſo their rebaptizing of their Sectaries, and the approbation of new mariages, the former wiues being yet aliue, doe ſpring from one bitter roote.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> Donatiſme.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Onatus</hi> a Sectarie firſt, after fell into grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous Hereſies, him the Browniſts haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4 Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> be affirmed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Sect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ries to be C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtians.</note> in full force, but they haue many other fautors and abettors that craftily fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the Schiſme, of the fire whereof they ſmell very ſtrong, the mantell of holineſſe couers all their
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21132:66"/> deſignes, ſo that few of them are found which wiſh not to ſeeme eyther better, or other men then they bee: When <hi>Hercules</hi> had loſt his Oxen, and had<note place="margin">Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>man in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Gods.</note> long time ſought them in vaine, they were at laſt diſcouered by their bellowing to be in <hi>Cacus</hi> denne: now <hi>Cacos</hi> in Greeke ſignifieth euill, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h draweth men backwards by the tailes as <hi>Cacus</hi> did the Oxen. For theſe men looke one way and goe another, like men that row on the water, or like Crabs on the land: Wee ſhould walke as our head Chriſt doth: but theſe men like the diſſeuered partes of a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nne ſeuerall wayes. There was a man that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his Mare to drinke, thought that hee ſaw the Moone drunke vp by his Mare, which indeed was onely hid and obſcured in a cloud; the next day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with his neighbours of Gotham, after much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aying of their cods heads together, it was concluded that they ſhould rip the mare &amp; let out the Moone: Euer ſince theſe Gothes or Goates haue thought all the world beholding to them for the recouery of the Moone: So in like manner, theſe Cathariſts thinke<note place="margin">Puritans.</note> all purity to haue beene borne, and ſhall die with them, and therefore ſay to euery man that will not ſpit iuſt as they doe, Touch mee not, I am holyer then thou. Stage-keepers in Cambridge with their viſards on, doe ſo long driue away euery man that they like not, till at the length they fill the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l ſo full, that fuller it could not haue beene, if they had called all commers: ſo with their ſeemely viſards of imagined ſeuerity, they doe ſo driue away bad men from their company, till at length they haue filled
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:21132:67"/> the ſcaffolds with hypocrites, &amp; the prophane with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breake the Chappell windowes, nay ſometimes breake downe both Chappell and Colledge, for when men ſee theſe leane prayers make ſuch fat faſts, they condemne firſt the profeſſors, and then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: T'is ſaid that in the Temple of <hi>Ianus</hi> there was the Image of <hi>Mars,</hi> of which I thinke theſe men are the Prieſts; for without they haue the double face of <hi>Ianus,</hi> and within nothing but <hi>Mars</hi> and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. II.</head>
                  <p>AN other meanes whereby theſe men inlarge their kingdome of Crickets, is Martiniſme or Libelling againſt iuſt authority: It is ſaid that <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> did euer anſwere Libels with Libels, neuer proceeded any farther, but as <hi>Dion</hi> ſheweth, hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forgaue a man but in ſhew: this ſeeming neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect is much imitated in Rome at this day, and <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> a military man is much commended for it, but <hi>Augustus</hi> a wiſe, and <hi>Tiberius</hi> a crafty Ptince, as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in times more peaceable, and their ſtate being ſomewhat litigious, did vſe more corraſiues to heale this ytching humor of Writing, not Satyrs or Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams, but theſe lawleſſe Libels that are written in bloud like <hi>Dracoes</hi> Lawes. <hi>Manlius</hi> that defended<note place="margin">Cicero pro Sex. Roſci. Amerin.</note> the Capitoll, was after by publike ſentence throwne downe from that hill, for that he had ſpread certaine ſlaunders, which did touch the famous <hi>Camillus:</hi> if
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:21132:67"/> many of theſe were ſo ſerued, or had their leggs bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as had the dogges, that did not onely barke, but bite them that came to the Temple; wee ſhould neuer haue heard of <hi>Martin Senior</hi> and <hi>Martin Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> with all that rimeleſſe and reaſonleſſe rabble of rayling Rabſhekes. To conclude, I would neuer haue this packe puniſhed, but eyther with ſilence, or<note place="margin">Camerina A loathſome fence in Sicilie.</note> with exemplarie iuſtice, if they be found out: for as I take it, all anſwere to them is impertinent, and doth but moue <hi>Camerina,</hi> which is againſt the Oracle: <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ne moueas Camerinam, immotam ſiſtere praeſtat.</hi> And againſt thoſe two verſes, vſde among vs for a by-word; <hi>Seu vineo, aut vincor,</hi> the reſt is too well knowne; for as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid, if an Aſſe kicke thee, wilt thou kicke him againe? I am perſwaded, nothing hath ſo much made them preſſe themſelues to death, and ſtand ſo often in white ſheetes, as for that they ſee learned men vouchſafing them an anſwere.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third diſeaſe of theſe men, is the greedy Worme, otherwiſe called couetouſneſſe, ſome call it the Dropſie, which if a man haue, hee will drinke of a cuppe as bigge as a Church; for theſe Cormorants vnder pretence of aboliſhing ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue deuoured vpp Church-liuings, whereby they make their Natiuity Pies the fatter; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, they would haue the Biſhops hyde (to vſe their owne wordes,) cut into many thongs, yea as
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:21132:68"/> many as <hi>Dido</hi> cut the Buls hyde into, when ſhe<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id. 1.</note> bought the ground of <hi>Iarbas,</hi> whereupon ſhee built Byrſa; again theſe men would haue all Tythes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Edo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>us.</note> to ſtipends and almes: thus would they ſerue the Church with baſe money, as wee did them in Ireland at the rebellion of Tyrone: a pleaſant man ſaid, that in their Church there was ſometimes <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia,</hi> but as the firſt letter of <hi>Caeſars</hi> name, being ſtricken of with thunder; there was left <hi>aeſar,</hi> which ſignifieth a God in the Hetruſcan tongue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting<note place="margin">Or Hetrurian.</note> that hee ſhould die, and bee Deified: ſo the firſt ſillable <hi>con</hi> being cut of, there was left <hi>ſcientia,</hi> making men like Heatheniſh Gods, knowing good and doing euill; at length comes the barbarous Barber and powles of <hi>ſci,</hi> (as the Amonitiſh King cutte the garments of <hi>Dauids</hi> Ambaſſadors by the middle) and there was left <hi>entia;</hi> that is wealth and large maintenance; now theſe men, as if they threw the caſt, called looſe all, for the Church, would ſweepe away <hi>entia</hi> without all conſcience, which I belieue will one day trouble them, as ill as<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ycoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on in Caſſandra.</note> 
                     <hi>Hercules</hi> did the Whale, when he was in the bellie of it: ſome haue wiſht the Sexton had beene in the Belfrey, when they drunke vp the Church, that ſo they might be neuer free from the belly ach, like the Melancholy man at Argos, that thought he alwaies heard Muſicke: others haue wondered, that they are not moleſted with the ſtone, hauing deuoured ſo many ſtones, as if they had the teeth of <hi>Saturne</hi> the God of Time, who eate a ſtone in ſteade of <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Athenaeus Dyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſta.</note> ſome ſuſpect that they haue a leather caſe for their
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:21132:68"/> tongues, becauſe they ſuppe vp ſuch hote broth, and haue no hurt, ſo that they may ſeeme to be chimnies not men, and if you will haue them liuing Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then are they Camels, which eate when they<note place="margin">Apoc. 19. 17</note> ſleepe: theſe are the birds of pray, which deuoure the fleſh of the Whore, that is, Abbies, Nunneries, and by conſequent, Colledges and Churches, as if they were Popiſh alſo: not vnlike one that ſaid, wee muſt eate no fleſh in Lent, becauſe the earth was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſt, of which it comes: as for bread and wine they come from the ſea, not from the earth, and had hee dwelt at Venice where nothing growes, he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken truely, thus theſe men call the long eares of the Hare hornes, that is they tearme Tythes, Iewiſh and Popiſh rytes, being ſomewhat of kinne to <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius</hi> the Elder, who tooke away <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den beard, ſaying it was vnfit, <hi>Apollo</hi> the Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her ſhould be beardeleſſe, and <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> his ſonne ſhould haue a beard; alſo that <hi>Apollos</hi> golden coate was too heauy in Summer, too colde in Winter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. IIII.</head>
                  <p>BEſides their practiſes, their opinions all bewray of what houſe they come; the name of Biſhoppe like learned <hi>Criticks,</hi> they turne into bite-ſheepe: the Litourgie into a Lethargie: the ſeruice they call the <hi>Starue vs,</hi> drawing here in the yoake with <hi>Barrow,</hi> for<note place="margin">The Romiſh Bee-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ue.</note> in <hi>Vliſſes</hi> Plough, were Aſſes aſwell as Horſes: here is all the difference, the Cathariſt like a Proteſtant,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:21132:69"/> skarde out of his wittes, ſtares as wildly vpon the Church as <hi>Agane</hi> did vppon her Sonne <hi>Pentheus</hi> when ſhee tooke him for a Bore: <hi>Ille mihi ferien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Metamor 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Aper, &amp;c.</hi> But the Browniſt hath a full frenzie, like the daughters of <hi>Praetus,</hi> that tooke themſelues for kine, and rageth like <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Aiax</hi> in the Tragedie, the former grants theſe opinions to bee true, but will not leape out of the Arke of <hi>Noah</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water: the other like the Rauen flies at large, and will not returne with the Doue: the one ſtaies in the houſe with as perfidious a mind as <hi>Ziba,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flatly runnes away like <hi>Agar,</hi> or the two ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of <hi>Shemei:</hi> but to proceede to their proper o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, they will haue Lay-Elders in the church, and widdowes, whereof the former implies a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction according to their owne doctrine, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that no lay man can bee Eccleſiaſtical, as they ſay, tis many times ſeene in the reformed Churches that a Ciuill Magiſtrate is one of the Lay-Elders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides how vnreaſonable is it, that he that neuer knew any difference, ſaue between Cow and Cow, ſhould<note place="margin">Lucian in iudicio Deorum.</note> for a yeare or two come to iudge of thoſe things, which a Synode or Councell could hardly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: but to amend the matter, they would haue all Councels and lawes aſwell Ciuill, as Canon, to be abrogated; to which deſire we anſwere, is <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuuius</hi> did at Capua, who when the people would haue had their Magiſtrates killed, deſired then firſt to agree vpon the election of new Officers, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple nominated diuers, but could agree of none, whereupon the Maſſacre was delaide, afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forgot:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:21132:69"/> ſo ſay I, let theſe men make vs new lawes in ſtead of the olde, elſe wee ſhall haue deformity in ſtead of vniformity. Oh what a ſtir haue they made about poſſeſſion and obſeſſion, queſtions of as little neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity as of great trouble, what is this, but to bring vp Guelphes and Gibelines againe, the Frigoſi and the<note place="margin">See the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ſtory.</note> Adorni, nay indeed the Guyſiard and the Condy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION. V.</head>
                  <p>ALl theſe tumults in religion come by impoſture of names: the Pagan takes Diuels for gods, therefore in America they worſhip the Diuell, leaſt he ſhould hurt them: the Turke dreames of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met as of a Prophet, not as a Couſener: as an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant husband oftentimes entertaines the Adulterer, that pretends kindred, in ſtead of kindneſſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his wife: the Iew fancies a Meſſias, in the letter for one in the ſpirite, like him that ſaide, <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> was a Saint, becauſe he was put in the Creed: The Greeke will haue pictures inſtead of Images, not vnlike our men that would not haue it called the Abſolution but the Remiſſion, in the booke of common Prayer, which deſire one compared to that of the men of Bengala, which are ſo afraide of Tygers, that they dare not call them by that name,<note place="margin">Doctor Boys in his notes vpon the Letany.</note> but by ſome more gentle, leaſt otherwiſe happily they might bee tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in peeces by them. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Wolfe talkes of Religion, meanes policie, like <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> that put out an Edict, wherein he ſignified,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:21132:70"/> that the Temples of the Gods, &amp; the Palaces of the Prince, were defiled by the common vſe of <hi>Vrine:</hi> therefore he appointed certaine places of marble, where this ſhould bee done, and that the fuller ſhould receiue the liquor, and pay tribute to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for his charges herein. Yong <hi>Titus</hi> ſaid it was ſordid, but the olde man wilde him to ſmell of the money, which he tolde him after came as tribute. The Arrian thinkes the three perſons in the Trinity are but three names, not vnlike the Poets that make Thebes in Aegypt with a hundreth gates; and Thebes in Greece with ſeauen gates to be all one, or like the old Chorographers that made Spaine a City, and the Ocean a riuer; ſo would theſe men circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe God within their ſhallow braines. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſt thinkes all thinges ſhould bee common, and therefore wiues, like the Fox, who hauing loſt her tayle, would haue had all the Foxes to cut off theirs, that by the publique calamity, ſhee might helpe her priuate ſhame; like bad Parliament men, who make motions for lawes in ſhew, but indeed for priuate gaine or grudge: ſo the men of this genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Herodotus in Clio.</note> hauing caſt of the vaile of their owne ſhame, like the wife of <hi>Candaules,</hi> moue other men to doe the ſame. The Barrowiſt like a drunken man calles his mother harlot, and will not dwell with her, if ſhee marry a new husband: nay, if ſhee will not ſweepe her houſe with the broome of Diſcipline, which hee will make or buy. The Cathariſts like a wilde Aſſe ſnuffes the wind in his noſtrils, as hee<note place="margin">Lycophron in Caſſandra.</note> runnes, and like <hi>Proteus</hi> King of Egypt, will neither
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:21132:70"/> goe by land nor ſea, but diggs a new way vnder the earth like a Mole; he likes nothing but that which is new, as our Dames doe with Cheries; or as the Romanes that would eat no fiſh, except they ſaw it ſwimme in the water and in the ſawce, the ſelfe ſame day. Tell them of ancient Fathers, and they will ſtoppe their noſe, and it may be their eares, as <hi>Vli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes</hi> did againſt the Syrens; but ſhew them a new Writer, though he were as factious as <hi>Cateline,</hi> and you ſhall pleaſe them aſwell as a Beare with hony. This is my Dreame and now I am awaked.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:71"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>FOlio 5. line 30. read hence for thence. f. 7. l. 21. reade Parelins for pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l. ns. f. 11. l. 10. r. Aolus for AEolus. f. 13. l. 19. r. Hitruians for Hetru. fol. 19. l. 4. r. Apozeme for a Pozeme. f. 29. l. 11. r. theſe for this. f. 37. l. 11. r. frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for infrugality. f. 41. Minetius for Minutius. f. 58. l. 3. r. Colocuntoſis for Cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuntoſis. f. 65. l, 14. r. are for and. f. 74. l. 4. r. quiſquis for quiſque f. 75. l. 15. r. Corbulo for Corbuto f. 87. l. 18. r. bawd for band. f. 103. l. 13. r. Hella for Hibla.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21132:71"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
